<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of the methods and motives of the late union and submission to the assembly offered and subscribed by Mr. Thomas Lining, Mr. Allexander Sheilds, Mr. William Boyd</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75377</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A324B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229748</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895682</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895682</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153033</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75377)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153033)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2341:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of the methods and motives of the late union and submission to the assembly offered and subscribed by Mr. Thomas Lining, Mr. Allexander Sheilds, Mr. William Boyd</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, MDCXCI. [1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153033:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT OF THE METHODS AND MOTIVES Of the late UNION AND SUBMISSION to the ASSEMBLY; Offered and Subſcribed BY
<list>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>THOMAS LINING,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>ALL EXANDER SHEILDS,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>WILLIAM BOYD.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Philip. 3.15.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Let us therefore as many as be perfect, be thus minded: And if in any thing ye be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reveal even this unto you.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, whereto we have already attained, let us walk by the ſame rule, let us mind the ſame thing.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, MDCXCI.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153033:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:153033:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:153033:3"/>
            <head>An Account of the Methods and Motives of the late <hi>Union</hi> and <hi>Submiſſion</hi> to the Aſsembly, offered and Subſcribed by Mr. <hi>Thomas Lining,</hi> Mr. <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Sheilds,</hi> and Mr. <hi>William Boyd.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>MONG other Characters that Commend <hi>Presbyterial Government,</hi> as the only Order and Plat form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which Chriſt Jeſus, the only Head and Lawgiver, hath inſtituted in His Church, above all other Forms, introduced by the Inventions and Uſurpations of Men; This is one, that it is the beſt Antidote for <hi>Schiſm,</hi> that ever was found: And where ever it is erected and exerted in its full Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Power, it brings all that acknowledge Subjection to it, unto <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> and <hi>Harmony</hi> keeps them in it, and reduces them into it, when it hath been broken. The Impreſſion of its Divine Authority, being ſo Authentick, that it enforces a Conviction upon all that have regard <hi>To the Law and the Teſtimony</hi> and extorts a Confeſſion from all, that have a Conſcience, that there is nothing in it, when eſtabliſhed, in its due Dimenſions, which may not and muſt not be ſubjected unto, (nay the greateſt of its Enemies, even the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> themſelves, thô they plead for many Additions, are forced to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that there is little or nothing in <hi>Presbytery,</hi> which is not of Divine Inſtitution, and which is not alſo admitted in their own Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thô depraved and corrupted by their audacious Additaments: And a challenge may be given, to all of them, to inſtance any thing in its whole Nature, Tenour, Order, Power, Rules, or Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that is not founded upon, deduced from, &amp; conſonant unto the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> Oracles) whereas there are ſeveral things in all other Forms of Government, which the more conſciencious a Man be, he will rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily be found the more heſitant to ſubmit to. The Eutaxie, comely Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and Beauty of this Ordinance of Chriſt (making the Church, both Comely and Terrible, and as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> compactly built) having likewiſe an attractive Vertue to allure all its Subjects and Members, to an ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Amity, and to conſtrain to Concord, as well as an Awful Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty (thô no way Magiſterial) to reſtrain from diviſive diſorders. And its courſe of Adminiſtration, being in ſuch a Gradation of Subordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of Inferiour Judicatories to Superior, that hardly can any Schiſm,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153033:4"/>have footing ere it be cruſhed, or rooting ere it be ſuppreſſed, when the Government is in its Integrity: Which was the reaſon rendered by K. <hi>Ja.</hi> the <hi>6th.</hi> why in <hi>Scotland</hi> there was ſo litle Hereſie, or Schiſm known. Hence whatſoever the Patrons of the <hi>Prelatick Hierarchy, Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiſts,</hi> who in this Symbolize, ſay to the contrary, in favours of <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy,</hi> as if it were the beſt expedient to prevent and remove Schiſm; And to the reproach of <hi>Presbytry,</hi> as if it were a Government, that did engender and encreaſe Diviſion and Schiſmatick Courſes: It is ſo well known in <hi>Scotland,</hi> that <hi>Prelacy</hi> is the Mother of Schiſm, and <hi>Presbytry</hi> the Medicine of it, that it needs not a laborious Probation. The <hi>Probatum eſt</hi> of 130 years experience, may ſerve inſtead of many Proofs. Let it be inſtanced ſince the Reformation, When was there ever <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> when <hi>Prelacy</hi> was eſtabliſhed? When was there ever <hi>Schiſm</hi> when <hi>Presbytry</hi> was redintegrated? When was there ever <hi>Concord</hi> when <hi>Presbytry</hi> declined? When was there ever any thing but <hi>Diſcord</hi> when <hi>Prelacy</hi> was on its aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant? Where or when was there ever a <hi>Diviſion</hi> which had not <hi>Prelacy,</hi> (or the Projects or Practiſes of thoſe that inclined and declined to it) for its cauſe and occaſion, riſe and ſpring? And how or when was it ever removed and remedied; and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> reſtored but by and under <hi>Presbytry?</hi> All the Diviſions and Breaches of this Church, from the Reformation to the year 1650, were occaſioned by, ſtated for, and continued only under <hi>Prelacy:</hi> And even that from thence to 1660, about the <hi>Publick Reſolutions,</hi> was ſtated upon, and occaſioned, abetted and continued, by the Projects and Practiſes of <hi>Malignants,</hi> ſtriving to ingyre themſelves, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to places of Power and Truſt, on deſign to re-introduce <hi>Prelacy.</hi> Which Diviſion then commenced, and at that time not cured, becauſe <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Government</hi> then declined, and the Authority of <hi>General Aſſemblies</hi> was then enervated, hath continued to this day, as the wretched Riſe of all our woful Rents, which hath racked, and almoſt ruined the Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, that adhered to the Reformation, who before that were as much feared and envied for Union, as ſince that, they have been flouted at, and deſpiſed for Diviſion, and yet want nothing to make them as much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired and reſpected as before, but to recover their former Union, by returning to their former Order, and repenting for their Deviations from it.</p>
            <p>But ſince the year 1660, the Riſe and Continuance of all our Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, either with the profeſſed Enemies of the Covenanted Reformation, or among the profeſſed Friends thereof, hath only flowed from the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpations and Impoſitions, of the <hi>Popiſh, Prelatical</hi> and <hi>Malignant</hi> Party,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153033:4"/>which ſome impoſed upon, complied with, and others oppoſed. And the only reaſon of their incureableneſs hitherto, hath been the want of <hi>Presbyterial Government</hi> in its full Force and Freedom: The happy Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution whereof in the meaſure it hath already arrived to ſince the Arrival and Advancement of King <hi>William</hi> to the Government of theſe Nations, under whoſe Patrociny, and <hi>in whoſe fight the Lord hath extended this Mercy, to give the</hi> Church <hi>this reviving, to ſet up the Houſe of our God, and to repair the Deſolations thereof, and to give us a Wall in our Judah</hi>) hath already reduced ſome who had continued in an abſtracted and ſeparate way for ſeveral years, unto Union and Communion with the reſt of their Breth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren in the Miniſtry, and hath engaged them into an orderly Submiſſion to the Authority of this Church, in all Her reſpective Judicatories. Which may gave ground of hope, that as this hath been the fruit of the firſt Aſſembly, after the Reſtoration of <hi>Presbyterial Government;</hi> So the re-din tegration thereof, is its full Vigor and Authority, and recovery of its former Faithfulneſs, and Zeal in Adminiſtration, in following Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, will through the Mercy of GOD, heal all remaining Breaches.</p>
            <p>But deſigning here to give a ſhort <hi>Relation</hi> of our Methods in proſecut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and our Motives that induced us to endeavour this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> It will not be amiſs, for the better underſtanding of the ſame, to hint a little more particularly, at the Cauſes, Means, and Meaſures of our Diviſions. They all proceeded, as was ſaid before, from the Uſurpation and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, of the <hi>Popiſh, Prelatical,</hi> and <hi>Malignant</hi> faction: For when <hi>Prelacy</hi> came in by force and fraud, and by the yeeldings of theſe that ſhould have ventured their All, in withſtanding its Introduction, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducers of it were enabled and encouraged, at their own leaſure and pleaſure, without control, to break down the Carved work of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and the Walls and Hedges and Legal Bul warks of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Laws</hi> and Solemn <hi>Covenants,</hi> that fenced it, with the Axe of an Act <hi>Reſciſſory.</hi> Some gave all the Countenance and Submiſſion then required by Law, to the Intruſion of <hi>Prelats</hi> and their <hi>Curats,</hi> by frequenting their Churches: Others thought it their duty to ſtand at a diſtance, and venture upon the hazard of diſobedience, in a Teſtimony againſt that ſin. When again they advanced the blaſphemous <hi>Supremacy,</hi> to its hight (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auctorating Chriſt Jeſus, of being only Head, King, and Lawgiver, to His Church, and declaring it to be a mortal Kings inherent right, to be Co-partner with Chriſt in that His incommunicable Prerogative) And by the uſurped Power thereof (preſuming they had now totally &amp; finally
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153033:5"/>overcome Chriſts Miniſters, and intending to flatter whom they could not hector out of their duty of contending againſt their Uſurpations) Obtruded a ſort of a Liberty, to ſome of them to Preach, under the Notion of an <hi>Indulgence,</hi> but ſuch as flowed from, ſtood upon, and was modified by the Supremacy: Some embraced this; others oppoſed and witneſſed againſt it. Laſtly when by wicked Oaths, Teſts and Bonds, impoſed to debauch Conſciences (which ſome inclined to comply with, or connive at; Others thought it neceſſary to teſtify againſt) a paſſage was prepared for the introduction of <hi>Popery:</hi> And a gap was opened for it, by the late <hi>Popiſh Toleration:</hi> Some thought it fit to purchaſe the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity and Liberty of Preaching by addreſſing for and embracing of it: Others durſt not have any thing to do with it, Nor forbear a Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny againſt it. Theſe Uſurpations with the defections flowing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, in Complyance therewith (while they ſtood as ſtumbling blocks and ſnares, and as we conceived as Idoles of jealouſie, in the entry of the Houſe of the Lord; So that we thought we could not have acceſs unto the Sanctuary, without being interprered, to give ſome reſpect or acknowledgement, or ſubjection, directly or indirectly, to thoſe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols and Incroachments, ſo diſhonourable to the LORD and offenſive to our Conſciences) did ſcar and deter us from Communion with many Godly, Reverend and Honoured Miniſters of this Church, ſo <hi>Indulged</hi> and <hi>Tolerated,</hi> in theſe Circumſtances, and obliged us to continue our Teſtimony againſt them, in an abſtracted way, when the Church was in that broken ſtate, deprived of the remedy of Church Judicatories, whereunto we might apply (in which caſe, we alwayes held there ſhould be no ſeparation without previous Application to them, and before their Judicial Sentence) And ween the caſe was ſo circumſtantiate, that we judged their Miniſtry, in the then exerciſe thereof, at that time, in the place where they Preached, under the Authority of the <hi>Indulgence</hi> and <hi>Toleration,</hi> could not be countenanced or concurred with by us, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out participating of the guilt of ſubmitting to, and ſymbolizing with Mens ſinful Encroachments. Yet we never owned a Poſitive or Active, Total or Stated Separation from the Church of <hi>Scotland;</hi> Or the Miniſtry thereof: Nor did we form ſeparate Churches under another Government or Miniſtry, diſtinct from, or independent upon the <hi>Presbyterial</hi> Church of <hi>Scotland;</hi> thô with this we were branded. Only for the time, we avouched a Negative, Paſſive, &amp; Conditional Abſtraction, from theſe Miniſters in the circumſtances above ſpecified: Not becauſe only we thought theſe were the Perſonal Sins of the Miniſters (for we alwayes declared our abhorrrance of that notion ſo deſervedly exploded by the learned Divines of this Church,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153033:5"/>that the Perſonal Sins of Fellow Worſhippers, Miniſters or Profeſſors, did pollute the Ordinances, or made Communion with them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſinful) but, becauſe we had reaſon to fear, they ſhould be our Sins, as well as theirs, if, as they had given the ſubmiſſion to theſe foreſaid Uſurpations required of them by Law, ſo we ſhould give the ſubmiſſion to them required of us by Law, by joyning.</p>
            <p>This was the caſe and cauſe of our Diviſions, until the Lord was pleaſed in our greateſt extremity, by ſending over King <hi>William,</hi> as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Inſtrument in His Hand, to reſcue us from <hi>Popery</hi> and Slavery, to remember this broken and bruiſed Church, and to give us a reviving in our Bondage, with a high Hand, and in a ſurprizing manner, and to remove our Yokes, under which we groaned, in a meaſure ſurpaſſing our expectations. By which Emergencies of Providence, in ſuch a manner, removing cauſes of our Diviſions, we could not but encourage our ſelves in the Hope, that the effects ſhould alſo be in time removed. And that He that healed our bruiſes from the yokes of long oppreſſing Enemies, might alſo lend His Hand and Help, to heal our Breaches of Diviſions with our diſſentient Friends and Brethren which we expected to obtain, if ever <hi>Presbyterian Government,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtick Aſſemblies,</hi> in that beautiful Order, ſhould be eſtabliſhed again in this Land, which we longed for, even for the recovery of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> as well as for other Advantages. In this Encouragement and Expectation, after ſome litle endeavours uſed in the opportunity of that Interregnum, to demoliſh and deſtroy the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Monuments of Idolatry, and to purge the Churches of the <hi>Weſt-Country</hi> of the <hi>Epiſcopal Curats</hi> we emitted an Apology at <hi>Douglas.</hi> The Tenour whereof here follows.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="proclamation">
                  <body>
                     <head>An Apology of the <hi>General Meeting</hi> of the United Societies of ſome <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> Diſſenting from, and Proteſting againſt the <hi>Toleration,</hi> for their Riſing and Continuing in <hi>Armes,</hi> in the preſent Juncture.</head>
                     <p>THE various Clamours and Conſtructions made of our Riſing in Armes at the time, and the reproaches of Diſorders, faſtned thereupon (thô in it ſelf innocent, and never intended by us, for the offence of any, but ſuch as all Zealous <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and good <hi>Patriots,</hi> will owne to be Enemies of GOD, and of all Mankind, and ſuch as we are under indiſpenſible obligations in our Places and Stations, to endeavour to ſuppreſs and extirpate; Yet becauſe it is our preſent unhappineſs, to have all our Actions miſconſtrued, and cenſured under the moſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153033:6"/>odious and invidious Character, that the Malice of ſome can put upon them) Do ſeem to require, for the vindication of our Teſtimony for the Cauſe of Chriſt, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneration of our ſelves, and removing any Jealouſies or Suſpicions, which through miſinformation, or prejudice any may conceive of us; That before we diſmiſs, We Declare to all concerned, That it is not by any Contrivance of ours, that we have either gathered, or continued in defenſive Armes hitherto, but have been drawn and called to it, by a ſpecial ſurpriſe of aſtoniſhing Providence. For, thô indeed, in the ſenſe of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſible and indiſputable neceſſity and expediency of giving ſome active Teſtimony againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> and of the duty of throwing down the Monuments of Idolatry (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly erected, and lately more and more encouraged under the Patrociny &amp; Protection of this Popiſh <hi>Toleration</hi>) we have been ſeveral times conſulting about ſome endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, in our poor Capacity to diſcharge that duty, with the leaſt tumult or trouble to the Country that was poſſible (not being able any longer to endure to ſee this purely Reformed and Covenanted Land, polluted again with Idolatry, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity of the Entycers thereunto, and thereby expoſed to the ineluctable Wrath of the Moſt High, without ſome witneſs of our indignation at the ſame) and thereupon had appointed this ſame concurrence of our Brethren, at this preſent <hi>Meeting,</hi> this ſame day, to conclude upon ſome Courſe to effectuate it; Yet as many of our Breth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, in ſeveral corners of the Land, without any Coreſpondence or Communication with one another, were animated and encouraged at one and the ſame time to ſet about this work, with others that the Lord ſtirred up to Zeal againſt Popiſh Idolatry: So the extraordinar Emergent, alarming the Country with fears and many reports, of the Papiſts intending and Attempting to raiſe fire and Sword through the Land, did prevent our appoyntments, and provoked us to go to Armes, for the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Religion, Lives, and Liberties, defence of the Country, and Relief of our Brethren, that lay neareſt the hazard then threatened and feared. In which poſture ſome of our Number, that were furtheſt remote, from the ſure intelligence of the truth of theſe Allarms, have continued hitherto, not being willing to diſperſe until by this Meeting formerly appointed, ſomewhat ſhould be concluded, with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent, as expedient for the preſent juncture, and emitted for their vindication from ſome diſorders, falſly imputed, and moſt grievous to us.</p>
                     <p>We do therefore further doclare, That whereas Reports have come to us, that ſome have robbed <hi>Gentlemen</hi> and ſome <hi>Epiſcopal Curats,</hi> of their Horſe and Armes, Money or Houſhold ſtuff. As for Horſe and Armes, taken in theſe Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuary Confuſions, if any be amongſt us, as we have endeavoured, ſo we ſhall endeavour Reſtitution: But as for money or any other thing robbed from theſe, we neither know the guilty perſons, nor are partakers with them, but do diſowne Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim and Deteſt all ſuch diſorderly and abominable practiſes. And further, the we owne and avouch it as our duty, bound upon us, from the Word of God, Solemn
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153033:6"/>Covenants, and Conſtitutions of this Church, to endeavour by all approven meanes, the Extirpation of <hi>Prelacy,</hi> as well as <hi>Popery;</hi> And therefore do reſolve through the Lords help, and as He ſhall give us Call and Capacity, to contribute our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt aſſiſtance, for the removing and diſpoſſeſſing the <hi>Prelatical Curats,</hi> from the Churches, upon which they are intruded: Yet we do not approve, nor ſhall we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the taking of any thing that belongs to them.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, we mean not now, nor whenſoever we may be conſtrained, or called to riſe in Armes defenſive, to wrong or encroach upon the Priviledges of any City, Burgh or Town whatſomever, or diſturb the Peace of the Country, either by Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, or continuing together in Armes unneceſſarly, to oppreſs either one or other: But as now we intend, ſo at any other time, when we are together, we ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs and go hame, and live in quiet ſo long as either Duty or Safety will permit us. For thô we be (through Grace) as ready as ever to ſuffer Perſecution, upon the ſame Heads of Truth, that we have hitherto contended for, and reſolve rather to loſs our deareſt blood, then to part with one hoof of them; And are as reſolute as ever to defend our ſelves &amp; all our Covenanted Bretheren, in the common Cauſe &amp; Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, againſt all Aſsaults of our Malignant Enemies; ſo far as we can reſiſt: Yet if they will forhear to perſiſt in their Perſecuting and Murdering us, for the time, we intend not to take or ſeek revenge of them, until we ſee what acceſs the Lord our Avenger, will give to a Legal Proſecution of them; Only this much oppoſition, they muſt expect, that we will not embodie with them, in any aſſociation for the Cauſe, which they have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed &amp; deſtroyed, nor with any other known &amp; avowed Enemies of Truth and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, Religion and Liberty. But ſince the Lord hath in His wonderful Providence (which we adore) raiſed up, helped and honoured the Illuſtrious <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> to be an Inſtrument in His Hand, of breaking in a great meaſure, the unſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Yoke of that <hi>Abſolute Tyranny,</hi> under which we have been long howling; As we pray the Lord, ſo to incline his Heart, to favour the Lords righteous Cauſe, and that he may pity and not permit, the yet remaining Ireacherous and Truculent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motters, Abettors, and Executioners of that <hi>Tyranny,</hi> to devour and deſtroy us any more: So we mind in due ſeaſon to remonſtrate to his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> the unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralelled <hi>Grievances</hi> and <hi>Severities,</hi> we have ſuſtained from them: And in the mean time, do our beſt, in dependence on the Lords ſtrength, to defend our ſelves againſt their Inſults:</p>
                     <p>Finally, we conclude, declaring our cordial and conſtant Adherence to the good Old Way and Cauſe of <hi>Scotlands</hi> Covenanted Reformation, in all its received and eſtabliſhed, Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Government, according to the Word of God, Confeſſion of Faith, Catechiſms, National Covenant, &amp; Solemn League, Solemn Acknowledgement of Sins and Engagement to Duties, Cauſes of Wrath, Acts of General Aſſemblies, both the ancient unrepealled Acts, and thoſe from <hi>1638.</hi>
                        <pb n="10" facs="tcp:153033:7"/>to <hi>1650.</hi> And all the Teſtomonies, Proteſtations, Remonſtrances, and Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, of old and of late, founded upon and conſonant to the ſame, againſt <hi>Popery, Prelacy, Eraſtianiſm, Sectarianiſm, Tyranny,</hi> and all the Encroachments of <hi>Abſolute Power</hi> over Laws and Liberties of Church and State either by <hi>Perſecution</hi> or <hi>Toleration.</hi> This in ſhort is the State of our Teſtimony, tranſmitted to us, from our renowned Anceſtors, ſealed by the Martyrs and Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of CHRIST, in our day; Which we hope the Lord will more and more Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate and Propogate to Poſterity.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Publiſhed at <hi>Douglaſs</hi> 
                           <date>the <hi>4<hi rend="sup">th.</hi>
                              </hi> of <hi>January,</hi> 1689.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>THereafter beginning to get more Converſe with ſome of our Brethren, which the violence of Perſecution precluded all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to before; And this Converſe begetting more deſires of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Amity with them: We intertained the firſt Motion from ſome of the Reverend Miniſters of <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> to confer with them about Points of Difference, and Methods of Compoſing them. The Conferences at that time, produced only ſome janglings, and at length ſome <hi>Overtures,</hi> tendered on both ſides, wherein we could not agree. Theſe Reverend Brethren propoſing (after ſome premitted Conſiderations preſſing the neceſſity of Union) <q rend="inline">That an Act of Oblivion be agreed upon for all Faillings, about points or Practiſes controverted among <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> ſince the year 1650, to this day; And that the Baſis of our Union, be the Holy Scriptures, ſenſed and applied, for the Reſolution of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted practiſes amongſt us, according to the laudable Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Cuſtoms, Practiſes, Acts of our National Aſſemblies, Books of Diſcipline, Gonfeſſion of Faith, Covenants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That caution be obſerved from all Reflections, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That after ſighting and approving their Ordinations and Licenſes, thoſe Miniſters and Preachers, who have formerly acted Independently upon their Brethren, preach Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giatly with ſome Miniſter ſettled in a <hi>Presbytry,</hi> for removing of former Stumblings.— And finally, that ſuch Failings be laid to heart, by all ſorts of Miniſters and Preachers, as they are convinced of, that they be ſet down in order, and pitched on as Cauſes of a Publick Faſt, and Humiliation upon ſome week day, through all the Meetings of <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> within this Kingdom, and that the Sins of the People, be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termixed among theſe Cauſes, <hi>&amp;c</hi>
               </q> This was the ſum of the <hi>Overtures</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered by theſe Reverend Miniſters, only in their own name, but they promiſed to meditate with the reſt of the Miniſters, for according thereunto. In Anſwer to theſe, we propoſed theſe <hi>Overtures</hi> premitting
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153033:7"/>alſo ſome Motives, together with the qualifications of the Union we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired) <q rend="inline">That the Baſis of our Union be the Word of GOD, Confeſſions of Faith, Covenants, Books of Diſcipline, Acts of General Aſſemblies, and the whole Contexture of the Order of this Church, before the <hi>Publick Reſolutions,</hi> in the pureſt Periods of this Church, which we may with one mind ſeek to have redintegrated. That we might ſearch and try our wayes, and Unite firſt in Confeſſing Sins, in keeping days of Humiliation for the ſame; Wherein we offered to Confeſs our Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, ſo far as we could be convinced any manner of way, that Church Judicatories ſhould appoint: And deſired the Miniſters from whom we differed, to Confeſs Doctrinally their Offences, that have been moſt ſtumbling, viz. <hi>Hearing the Prelatical Curats,</hi> the <hi>Late Indulgence, Addreſſing for, and Accepting of the Toleration,</hi> &amp;c And concur in procuring the Condemnation of theſe things, in Eccleſiaſtick Aſſemblies. That the <hi>Covenants</hi> might be Renewed, with accommodation to our times-and a Solemn Acknowledgement of the publick Breaches, and Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Duties thereof, applied to the preſent day. That to pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vent all future Diviſions, the former Offences might never hereafter be complied with, under pain of Church Cenſures, nor any other Mould or Model of <hi>Presbyterian Government,</hi> than what was eſtabliſhed between the years 1638 and 1650. Nor any State Contrivance or Conſtitution whatſoever, be admitted or ſubmitted unto, which may infer a recognizance of any <hi>Eraſtian</hi> Uſurpation. That in the mean time, the Miniſters ſettled in Paroches, under the late <hi>Indulgences</hi> and <hi>Toleration,</hi> might declare, that now they have another Holding, than either of theſe; And that they now officiate in places where they are fixed, according to the old <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Order. And finally, that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours ſhould be uſed to check and ſuppreſs the Foments, that nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and encreaſe Diviſion, on either hand, as heart Animoſities, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienations of Affection, Paſſion, Prejudice, Jealouſies, receiving and reporting Miſinformations, and all other things of that nature tending thereunto.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Mutual <hi>Overtures,</hi> being refered to farther Conſideration, we thought it a good Expedient, both to promot and direct a deſirable Union with our Brethren, <hi>to Renew the Covenants,</hi> with a publick Accknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, both of their and our breaches thereof, and Engagement, to the Duties of the Covenants, with accommodation to our preſent Circumſtances; which we Solemnly Accompliſhed at <hi>Leſmabego March</hi> 3. 1689. In the <hi>Acknowledgement,</hi> we confeſs with relation to bygone dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153033:8"/>(<hi>Art.</hi> 2. <hi>Page.</hi> 56.) <q rend="inline">That as many by defection, both in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance with Prelacy and Eraſtianiſme, hath broken the Churches beauty and Bands, Order, and Union, in making a faction repugnant to her eſtabliſhed Order, and cenſurable by her ſtanding Acts, in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Novations in the Government, and making a rent in the bowels of the Church, by cauſing Diviſions, and Offences, contrare to the Doctrine of this Church, have made themſelves guiltie of Schiſm; So others on the other hand have upon ſlender and unſufficient Grounds, ſeparate both from Miniſters (even the moſt Faithful and Zealous, and ſuch as were not chargeable with Complyances) and from Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian Societies and Families, becauſe of Differences in judgement, in incident debates, not neceſſary, nor material, nor wherein the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Chriſt was much concerned, or becauſe of perſonal Offences, eaſily removed, not obſerving the Rules of Chriſt, for removing them, nor having reſpect to His great Commands of Charity, forbearance, forgiving one another, or condeſcendency: And between divided Parties, which in our day, have long been byting and devouring one another, there hath been too much both of ſinful Union and Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, in terms prejudicial to Truth and Duty, on the one hand, and of ſinful Heats, Animoſities, Jealouſies, Pride, Paſſion, and Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, on the other hand; Grieving the Spirit of GOD, eating up the Power, and much hindering the holy Practice and ſpiritual Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Religion. And too much alſo of ſowing diſcords among Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and promotting our Contentions by too credulous and ſedulous taking up, &amp; ſpreading reports &amp; reproaches one of another.</q> And in our Renewed <hi>Engagement</hi> to Covenant Duties, with relation to preſent differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Union with our Brethren, we declared our reſolved Endeavours and Vowes, <q rend="inline">On the one hand to labour to recover and preſerve the Liberty and Purity of the Worſhip of God, from all Corruptions, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations and Inventions of Men, <hi>Popiſh, Prelatical, Eraſtian,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; And if we could not gett thoſe Corruptions reformed or remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, to ſtudy to keep our ſelves free of Communion and Participation with the ſame, (according to <hi>Artic.</hi> 1. §. 2. <hi>Pag.</hi> 68.) And to refuſe, withſtand, and witneſs againſt all Encroachments on the Liberties of this Church, in all time coming; And withdraw our ſelves from Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with all ſuch Meetings and Congregations, that hold their Freedom from, &amp; are modified by ſuch Uſurpations (as <hi>Indulgences</hi> and <hi>Tolerations,</hi> according to <hi>Artic.</hi> 2. §. 3. <hi>ibid.</hi>) And on the other hand, That we ſhall guard againſt all Schiſm and ſinful Separation, or unjuſt,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153033:8"/>raſh, and diſorderly withdrawing from Congregations, Societie, <hi>&amp;c</hi> or any part of the Communion of the true Reformed Covenanted. Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> holding purely and intirely the Doctrine, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Diſcipline and Government of the ſame, in Principle and Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, according to the Rules of Chriſt, and ſtanding Acts and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of this Church: And that we ſhall neither gather nor ſet up formed ſeparate Churches or Societies, under other Ordinances, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment or Miniſtry, diſtinct from the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Church of <hi>Scotland;</hi> Nor withdraw from Miniſter or Member of that Body, for any offence in any Caſe, where either the Offence may be Legally removed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our withdrawing,—or is a thing to be condeſcended on, forborn, or forgiven: But ſhal ſtudy to maintain <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> &amp; <hi>Communion</hi> in Truth &amp; Duty, with all the Miniſters and Members, of the ſaid Church that do, and in ſo far as they do follow the Inſtitutions of Chriſt (As in <hi>Artic.</hi> 2. §. 4. <hi>Pag.</hi> 69.) And in <hi>Artic.</hi> 6. <hi>Pag.</hi> 71. We engage that we ſhall likewiſe deſire, deſign and endeavour to get the defections, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Neutralities, and unhappy diviſions, that have long and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentably wounded and wrecked the Church removed, Differences ſettled and breaches healed, in ſuch a way and upon ſuch termes, as may be Honourable and Advantageous for the Cauſe. And if our Brethren and we, between whom ſuch Differences have fallen in, and have been ſadly Fomented on all hands, will ſearch and try our ways reſpectively, how far they and we have receded from the good old way of the Church of <hi>Scotland.</hi> And in our impartial ſearch ſhall find out our reſpective defections, and breaches of Covenant, on the one hand, and on the other, and unite in confeſſing theſe, by joyning, in this, or the like Acknowledgement of publick Sins, and keeping dayes of humiliation, and mourning for the ſame. And as we offer and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to confeſs our Sins here acknowledged, or any other ſo far as we can be convinced, any manner oſ way, that they ſhall deſyre or appoint; So if they, at leaſt will confeſs theirs Doctrinally, and they and we both forſake them mutually, and forſaking concur in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing the Condemnation of them, in Eccleſiaſtick Synods or Aſſemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and ſo return unto, and fix our ground on the old Eſtabliſhed foundations, according to the Word of God, and Conſtitutions of this Church ſettled, before the Covenanted Reformation ſtopped, We will then embrace and maintain Union and Communion with them and ſubmiſſion to them in the Lord: And ſhall not ſuffer our ſelves, Directly or undirectly, by whatſoever Combination perſwaſion or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153033:9"/>terror, to be divided or withdrawn, from this bleſſed Union and Conjunction.</q> Thus far we advanced in theſe ſteps with one accord.</p>
            <p>Thereafter, in the remembrance of theſe Reſolutions and Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which we looked upon, as at laſt inferring an obligation lying u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon us, to make ſome Endeavours, in purſuite of this Union, which is a Duty, Materially, Morally, and Antecedently obliging in it ſelf: Being invited alſo by ſome reverend Miniſters in <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> we had once &amp; again Conferences with them: Wherein at length after we had ſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted on the neceſſity of confeſſing and condemning theſe Defections and Corruptions, which cauſed us to ſtand ſo long at a diſtance from them, &amp; propoſed the Difficulties we had in our Conſcience, to return to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them before theſe were removed, as is ſaid. They conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended upon ſome Expedients for our ſatisfaction, that it ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to us, to exhibite to the next <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> our <hi>Teſtimony</hi> againſt all theſe courſes and practiſes in Miniſters, that did offend us, and to plead for recording of it, in the Books of Aſſembly, which might exoner our Conſciences, and abſolve us from all participation with, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in the guilt, that we conceived to be in any of theſe things.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, taking this Condeſcenſion to further conſideration (which indeed gave us more clearneſs than we had before) and declining any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther procedure in it, until we conſulted the mind of the People, whom we deſired to be tender of, and guard againſt all appearance of impoſing upon them, or overdriving them, unto things they could not be ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clear in. We had a Meeting with them, to deliberate upon this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, at <hi>Dowglas,</hi> wherein we propoſed the Caſe, and offered ſeveral Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations to bring things to a temper, endeavouring to ſatisfie and ſolve ſeveral Scruples and Objections, adduced by tender, zealous, and ſerious People; Alleaging they could not have freedom or clearneſs to joyn with theſe Miniſters, from whom they had formerly withdrawn, until they ſhould acknowledge their defection, for without that, they could never be counted faithful, &amp; would never faithfully urge others to confeſs their Sins, when they would not acknowledge their own: And that Union without this, would bury the Teſtimony againſt theſe defections. And ſeveral other difficulties of this nature, very weighty to them, and affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us. To all which we endeavoured to give ſolution, by ſhewing, That the not confeſſing of Sins, not in preſent practiſe, was never, and can never be owned by us, to be a ground of Separation; And that we found in Scripture, the Godly had Communion in Churches, where there were ſeveral Corruptions not confeſſed nor reformed. And that if the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153033:9"/>Church came to recover Her Authority and Aſſemblies, we muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and unite in Reformation, and would not be required to unite in defection; telling them alſo of the forementioned Condeſcenſion, and of our purpoſe to give in Papers to the firſt Aſſembly. And perſwading them, (thô we would not urge them againſt their Conſcience, to hear all, or any of the Miniſters, againſt whom there were greateſt exceptions) to try and ſearch through all the Country, where ſuch might be had, that were moſt free of theſe offences, or moſt faithful in confeſſing them, and joyn with theſe, in the firſt place. In the mean time, becauſe it was a grave and greatly important matter, not raſhly to be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, we agreed that a day of Humiliation ſhould be ſet a part, for pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Light in the caſe; And that the buſineſs ſhould be ſuſpended to another Meeting.</p>
            <p>Thus the Matter was kept in ſuſpence, for a conſiderable time; And in the mean while, we were now and then upon occaſion, in conference, and ſometimes in preaching, pleading for endeavours of Union; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in perhaps our weakneſs, ſometimes hath vented it ſelf in expreſſions of too great fervor, to the offence of tender People; as formerly it might have its Eruptions, to the offence of others, in the proſecution of our differences with them. And in ſeems (thô the manner of managing a buſineſs, ſhould not prejudge People againſt the matter it ſelf, yet) ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral have been ſtumbled upon this. For at the next Meeting, at the forſaid place, ſome did move in the debate with more fervour, than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, againſt Union, except the foreſaid defections were confeſſed. And other Objections and Scruples were adduced, both verbally and in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, ſent from ſeveral Societies, bearing they could not return to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining party, until they ſhould return from their declinings; And that confeſſion and forſaking of Sin, is ſo frequently inculcate in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that without this, they could not expect the bleſſing of God, upon the Miniſtry of thoſe who retained and defended cauſes of wrath; And that the Church was not yet ſettled, and the Government not yet eſtabliſhed, &amp; ſo they could not tell, but their might be Corruptions in the very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of it. Whereunto we offered ſeveral Anſwers, and at the cloſe of that Meeting, it was earneſtly deſired by the People &amp; promiſed by us, that, ſome thing ſhould be write, and ſpread amongſt them, that might inform them, and clear from the Scriptures, the difficulties of this controverſie, &amp; the neceſſity of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> &amp; <hi>Communion</hi> with the Church in the preſent circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; Which accordingly ſo ſoon as was poſſible, was prepared, and may be hereafter publiſhed. Afterwards the buſineſs was more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153033:10"/>followed, both ſides being more abſtract, and kept in ſuſpence, waiting to ſee the conſtitution of the Church eſtabliſhed, and a free <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſembly,</hi> unto which they might make application, whence all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected more light and reſolution would accrue. At length, the <hi>General Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly</hi> indicted by Authority approaching, we had another Meeting, in which after ſome litle debates, we came to a more ſedate agreement, to apply to the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and that we ſhould give in Papers to them: We told them that we had a mind, after exhibition of our <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the Defections that offended us, to Submit and Unite; &amp; per-ſwaded them to do the like; But they were reſolute to ſuſpend offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Submiſſion and Union, untill they ſhould underſtand, what notice the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> would take, and what uſe they would make, of our Papers. Upon this we concluded to give in our Papers, and agreed to ſet a part a day before the ſitting of the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> to pray for Counſel and Conduct from the Lord, in proſecution of this affair.</p>
            <p>Before this time, thô we had in ſeveral places, and at ſeveral times given a Specimen of our inclinableneſs to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> and intenſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient deſire of Communion with our Brethren, in joyning with ſome, both in the North and South, to ſhew that we did not ſcruple now, to incorporate with them, when the grounds of Separation were taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: Yet hitherto we ſuſpended Submiſſion and fixed Union, until the Metting of the <hi>General Aſsembly,</hi> both becauſe, this was a matter proper for an <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> the differences concerned the whole Church, and could only be cognoſced upon, and compoſed by an <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties concerned in them, diſperſed through a great part of the Church, could apply or anſwer to no Judicatory, inferiour to an <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the whole; Therefore we thought it proper and expedient, to depoſitate our <hi>Teſtimony</hi> there, and ſo take occaſion to make our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> as publick, as our diviſion was: And indeed our intention to Addreſs the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> was almoſt as univerſally known, at leaſt through the <hi>Weſt</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> as our differences were, thô our deſign in the Addreſs was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to many. For both in travelling through the Countrey towards <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and when we came there, we found very many and multifa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious opinions and reports of it: Some of a Malignant temper, telling that we were come to fire the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and create confuſion among them: Others, that we had a mind to give in Papers declining their Authority, and proteſting againſt their Conſtitution and Proceedings: Some alleag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing litle leſs, then we had got Gold from the <hi>Jacobites</hi> and <hi>Prelatiſts,</hi> to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153033:10"/>ſow diſcord among them: Others expreſſing their wiſhes and hopes that for our former Practiſes, and preſent Purpoſes and Papers, they ſhould ſee us well paid home, and made to confeſs on our knees, our ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Schiſm, and to ſubject to the ſeverity of Cenſure, when we had done all. Yea even among the beſt affected towards us, both Miniſters and others, whom we conſulted in the Affair, we found thô they had Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for the deſign of the Workers, yet they had a great jealouſie of the end of the work it ſelf.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> having ſat ſeveral <hi>Seſſions,</hi> our Paper, and the purpoſe of it, was motioned in the <hi>Committee of Overtures,</hi> before it was fully prepared; And the Motion favourably intertained by that Reverend Committee, they were pleaſed to appoint a Subcommittie of their Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to ſee it, and confer with us about the contents of it, who after hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it read, did object little againſt the matter of it, but did urge the ſmoothing of it, and that we ſhould take out ſome particulars, that might irritate and offend ſome, that would look upon themſelves as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriouſly reflected upon by them, which might provoke heats, and ſtop all other buſineſs, whence the Church might ſuſtain great diſadvantages, and our ſelves have litle peace; We anſwered, we could not yeeld to the expunging of any particulars in it, which were matters of offence, and underſtood by us to be Corruptions, which our purpoſe was to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt, without any deſign to irritate any by Reflections: And if any ſhould be provoked to raiſe heats, we ſhould be ſorry for it, but we could not foreſee how any could riſe to that hight, as to brake the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblyes</hi> Harmony, ſince we were reſolved to ſeek concord, and not Contention: And what ever they ſhould do with the paper, if we might once have acceſs to table it, our Contention would be at an end, for then our Teſtimony would be given in, and lye at their door, to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as they ſhould think fit, which would exoner our Conſcience, and declare to them, as the Repreſentatives of the Church, that our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Church at preſent, could not infer an approving of what we condemned before, nor a condemning of what we approved before. Theſe things being favourably repreſented to the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittee of Overtures, they added ſome Reverend Brethren to the Subcommittee, to whom it was read a ſecond time: They told us, they feared it would not be well received, and that it might have bad effects, if it ſhould be read, but deſired to know further what we reſolved to do, if it ſhould be rejected: We anſwered, we would ſtill adhere to it, and could not change our Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments about the things contained therein; Yet becauſe the things in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153033:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>teſtified againſt in the paper, were not in the preſent Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church, and therefore our <hi>Submiſſion</hi> at preſent, could not be looked upon, to be an Homologation of the things therein witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt; Therefore if we be allowed to exhibite our <hi>Paper</hi> to this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> we would ſtand to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> and <hi>Submiſſion,</hi> therein offered, let them diſpoſe of it as they will. They further deſired there might be a ſhort Paper drawn, to introduce the larger, ſhewing the ſcope of it, and out deſign in it: which we did, and therein made an offer and promiſe of Union and Submiſſion, after the Exhibition of our foreſaid <hi>Teſtimony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Papers</hi> both larger and ſhorter, being preſented to the <hi>Committee of Overtures:</hi> After ſome Debate, they condeſcended to hear both Read: which done; after our removal a little, The Moderator told us the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the Committee, <hi>That they were ſenſible the large paper contained many ſad Truths in it, but upon ſeveral weighty Conſiderations did judge it in convenient to preſent it to the</hi> Aſſembly, <hi>becauſe of ſome Miſtakes, Reflections and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>npracticable</hi> Overtures <hi>it it:</hi> To this, we could accord, but urged the giving of it in; whereupon it was recommitted to the Subcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, with an addition of more Members, inſtructed to labour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us to ſiſt, and move no more in it. Their Endeavours and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments not prevailing with us, we were again called before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Overtures; And preſſed to condeſcend, and reſt content, that the Papers were exhibite to them, and read before them: We anſwered we could not, except the Reverend Committee, would aſſume to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or get devolved upon them, the power of the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> to cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſce on the matter, then we would ſiſt; Otherwiſe our buſineſs was with the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> and therefore we pleaded that the Papers might be tabled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. Hereupon they Condeſcended to tranſmit them, with Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures prepared concerning them, that we ſhould be received, that the Large Paper ſhould not be read, for ſeveral reaſons <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Next day both <hi>Papers</hi> were exhibited in open <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> The ſhort Paper was read, with the Overtures of the Committee concerning the Large one. The matter coming to a vote, Some propoſed the State of it thus, <hi>Read the Large Paper or not;</hi> Others thus, <hi>Approve the Overtures concerning it or not.</hi> Its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly believed the <hi>Vote</hi> went ſo, which hath ſtumbled many; we being removed knew not how it was expreſſed, but when ſome of us challeng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it afterwards, as being very illegal, to vote a Paper ſhould not be read, for reaſons giving a Character, and Condemning the Paper, when the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> knew not what was in the Paper; a Reverend Miniſter and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153033:11"/>Member of the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> aſſured us, that the vote did not go ſo, but that it was propoſed in the laſt place, and Condeſcended to, that it ſhould be voted thus, <hi>Approve the firſt Overture,</hi> (touching our being received) <hi>and the other</hi> (that the Paper ſhould not be read) <hi>or not,</hi> without men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning of the reaſons. The whole Aſſemblie voted <hi>Approve, Nemine contradicente.</hi> We being again called before them, the <hi>Moderator</hi> exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted us to <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi> To which one of our number made a ſhort Reply, wiſhing the Venerable <hi>Aſſembly</hi> had thought it fit to read the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, but ſeeing it could not be obtained, ſuch was our love to <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> that we would ſubmit, but as to the reaſons given for the not reading it, becauſe of the Miſtakes and Reflections in it, we were not conſcious of any ſuch thing: And deſiring that it might be on Record, that ſuch a Paper was exhibited, which accordingly was Minuted. There was only one more of us then preſent, who, after his Brother had concluded in a few words, offered to ſpeak, and at greater length, to enlarge his Reply to ſome things expreſſed by the Reverend <hi>Moderator</hi> in his Exhortation. But it ſeems that ſome of the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> had a ſuſpition, that poſſibly he might, in his accuſtomed fervor, bring forth ſomething, that might have been irritating: (which yet he was ſo far from deſigning, that he had reſolved and premeditate, to ſay nothing, but what might corroborate &amp; juſtifie the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> and to ſhew what were his Inducements to it, and how conſiſtent it was with his former Principles and Practiſes:) For, when he offered to ſpeak, the <hi>Moderator,</hi> and others alſo, requeſted him to forbear: Whereunto he yeilded, not at all ſuſpecting or foreſeing that any would ſtumble at this ordinary piece of Diſcretion; at which we underſtand ſince, that ſome Friends have been offended, interpreting this Silence to have been a receeding from our <hi>Teſtimony.</hi> But Truly, as he had intended not to have been ſilent, and if he had thought this could have been ſtumbling to any, would rather have ventured upon the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his Diſcourſe, then to be ſo miſconſtructed for his ſilence: So, conſidering the <hi>Aſſemblies</hi> reiterate urging him to forbear, (by way of Requeſt, not of Command) and how neceſſarie Condeſcention is in theſe Circumſtantials of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> what his Brother alſo had ſaid before him, and how there was no other <hi>Teſtimony</hi> ever deſigned by us, but that in the Larger Paper exhibited in write, he did not think, he was called to contend for ſpeaking any more at that time.</p>
            <p>This is the true, ſhort, and yet full <hi>Narrative</hi> of the whole Tranſaction which we thought needful to publiſh, in all the particulars of it, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the falſhood of the various miſreports induſtriouſly ſpread of it, by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153033:12"/>thoſe that envy the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of Presbyterians,</hi> reflecting upon the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> as well as reproaching us, and impoſing upon the People, who are infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſometimes, that the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> carried very imperiouſly, in impoſing upon us, as the condition of our being received, to confeſs on our knees, many Errors and Extravagances, in witneſſing againſt theſe Courſes, we called Corruptions, and to condemn and renounce all our Teſtimonies. And that we reſiled and receded from every point, for which we could contend with a great deal of clamor on the Hills, but had nothing to ſay when we came before the <hi>Aſſembly.</hi> And ſometimes again, that we car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried very inſolently before them, and in our Paper upbraided the whole <hi>Aſſembly.</hi> And yet others interpret our condeſcending to the <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of the Paper as aboveſaid, to be a betraying and burying of it, and the Teſtimony that's in it, againſt the ſins of the Land. To confute all which Calumnies, and to ſubmit our Papers to the cenſure of all that will take notice of them, as we have offered them to the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Church Repreſentative, we ſhall here ſubjoin the Papers themſelves.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>The SHORT PAPER.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>To the <hi>Moderator</hi> and <hi>Remanent Members</hi> of the <hi>General Aſſembly</hi> of this <hi>CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH.</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WIth the greateſt earneſtneſs of longing we have deſired, and yet with a patience perhaps to exceſs, we have waited for an Opportunity, to bring our unhappy Differences (of which, all Parties concerned are wearie) to a happy and holy cloſe: And for this end to have acceſs to apply our ſelves to a full and free <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Aſſembly</hi> of this Church, inveſted with Authority and Power, <hi>in foro Divino &amp; Humano,</hi> to determine and cognoſe upon them. The want of which an <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> conſtitute in that Vigor, to which through the Mercy of GOD, this <hi>Venerable National Synod</hi> hath arrived, hath been the great let and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment of our compoſing the ſaid Differences, in a way wherein not only we, but all of the ſame Sentiments would Acquieſce. Now having obtained this much longed, and long prayed for Priviledge, We cannot forbear any longer humbly, to Accoſt and Addreſs this <hi>Venerable Aſſembly,</hi> with a free and ingenuous Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Minds and Deſires: The ſcope of which is to Repreſent thoſe things, which have been moſt ſtumbling to us, for the Exoneration of our Conſciences; And to declare our Deſign, after we have exhibited our <hi>Teſtimony</hi> againſt theſe Courſes, which we underſtand to have been Corruptions and Defections in this Church, and laid it down at the <hi>Aſſemblies</hi> feet, to be diſpoſed of, as their wiſdom ſhall think
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153033:12"/>fit, That we ſhall in all required Submiſſion, ſubject our Selves, our Lives, and Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, to the Cognizance of the Judicatories of this Church, and ſhall equally oppoſe Schiſm and Defection, in any Capacity, that we ſhall be found capable of. And here by theſe Preſents, we bind and obliege our Selves, faithfully, to live in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, and Communion, intire ſubjection, and due Obedience, in the LORD, to the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of this Church, in her Reſpective Judicatories; As witneſs our hands at <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Tho. Lining. Al. Sheilds. Will. Boyd</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>The LARGER PAPER.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>To the <hi>Moderator</hi> and <hi>Remanent Members</hi> of the <hi>General Aſſembly,</hi> now Conveened at EDINBURGH.</salute>
                     <argument>
                        <p>The Humble <hi>Propoſals</hi> of Mr. <hi>Thomas Lining,</hi> Mr. <hi>Alexander Sheilds,</hi> and Mr. <hi>William Boyd.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </argument>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IF our Eye could ſutably affect our Hearts this day, <hi>Right Reverend,</hi> we might find much matter, both of Rejoycing and Mourning, in the wounderful Commencement and Advancement of this <hi>Work of Reformation.</hi> As at the <hi>Jews</hi> return from <hi>Babylon</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Prieſts and Levites, and all the People ſhouted with a great ſhout, when they praiſed the LORD, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the foundation of the Houſe of the LORD was laid; Tet ſome of them, that had ſeen the firſt Houſe, wept with a loud voice, ſo that the People could not diſcern the noiſe of the ſhout of joy, from the noiſe of weeping. So at this time, we are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to rejoice, with thanksgiving for, &amp; we ſhould indeed be very ungrate and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, if we did not acknowledge with Praiſe and Admiration, the Mercy of God, which endureth for ever, manifeſted &amp; magnified in the progreſs of this Work hitherto; That at the time appointed of God, the leaſt expected by us, at the time of our greateſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, and our Enemies greateſt inſolency, the Lord hath been pleaſed in Sovereign Mercy, inſtead of overtaking us with judgements threatned for our ſins, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out waiting on our Repentance and Preparations, by turning unto Him, to prevent and ſurprize us, not only, with an outward enlargement of Reſt and Peace, without prejudice to Truth, in a way, wherein we are not beholden, to the enſnaring favours of his Enemies, but with ſuch a reviving in our bondage (in the midſt of Wrath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membering Mercy) brought about by the repreſſion of <hi>Tyranny,</hi> ſuppreſſion of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> and depreſſion of <hi>Prelacy,</hi> as that we have yet a Nail in His Holy Place, to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153033:13"/>ſet up the Houſe of our GOD; Yea the Altar alſo is ſet again upon His Baſes, and the daily burnt Offerings are offered by number, according to the cuſtom, and the foundation of the Temple is laid again: When the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of this Church is aſſerted, and the <hi>Confeſſion of Faith</hi> formerly received, is read, voted, approven, and eſtabliſhed by Parliament, and even ſeveral controverted Truths formerly much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and obſcured, under a load of many Calumnies, are now juſtified and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated; The <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> of Chriſt, are adminiſtred in great Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Plenty, and Peace; The <hi>Government</hi> of Chriſts Inſtitution, by <hi>Kirk Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Presbiteries, Synods,</hi> and <hi>General Aſſemblies,</hi> ſo long born down, is at length reſtored to what it was <hi>Anno 1592.</hi> And all Acts &amp; Laws contrary or preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial unto, inconſiſtent with, or derrogatory from <hi>Presbyterial Government</hi> are reſcinded, with this honour, that it is declared by Act of Parliament, that this is the <hi>Government</hi> moſt agreeable to the Word of GOD, and moſt conducible to the advancement of true Piety and Godlineſs, and eſtabliſhment of Peace and Tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity within this Realm: And the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> retrieved to ſuch a fond of Freedom, that all Eccleſiaſtick Courts, may without reſtraint, or being accountable to any Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped Power in the Magiſtrate, aſsert all the Authority, and exerce the Power, wherewith Chriſt hath entruſted them. Which power if duely and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly improved, and put in execution, may through the Bleſſing of GOD contribute very much to the reducing <hi>Order,</hi> &amp; the redreſs of many <hi>Diſorders</hi> in this Church. And now alſo the cauſes of our Diſunion &amp; Diviſion in times of defection, being in a great meaſure removed, when <hi>Eraſtian</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations are abrogated, the Churches intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick Power redintegrated, and the Corruptions introduced by Complyances, ſo far abdicated and antiquated, that they are not in the conſtitution of the Church, and do not continue to be the ſcandal and ſnare of the times: We hope and expect a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy may be found for the Breaches and Diviſions, that we thought incurable, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and communion in the Lord may be attained. But thô for theſe things we be called to rejoice, yet we are no leſs obliged to mourn, when we obſerve this Houſe of the Lord, ſo unlike the former, wanting many things, the former had, and peſtered with many things the former wanted. As at the building of the ſecond Houſe, after the Captivity of <hi>Babylon,</hi> they that had ſeen the firſt Houſe wept with a loud voice, when they obſerved its Conſtitution and Structure, ſo far ſhort of the former, for Order and Beauty, and wanting ſome glorious Prerogatives the other had; as the <hi>Urim and Thummim, the Fire from Heaven, the Ark of the Teſtimony,</hi> &amp;c. So, they that have ſeen our former <hi>Reformation</hi> in its Integrity, before the late Deformation, can hardly refrain from weeping at the ſight of the ſad, diſproportion, between this and the former. In the former, as the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was calculate in the neareſt conformity to the Divine Pattern; ſo the Builders, had always a care to pull down what was to be demoliſhed, before they eſtabliſhed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153033:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>what was to ſtand, and to purge away the rubbiſh from the Foundation, before they promoved the Superſtructure: Accordingly when <hi>Prelacy</hi> was reintroduced at ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times, the firſt thing they did when they recovered their power, was alwayes to exert it in condemnation of that Corruption, and of theſe <hi>Aſſemblies</hi> and <hi>Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> that promoved, abetted, favoured, or complied. And when the <hi>Era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtran Supremacy</hi> began to encroach upon the Churches Liberties, and to bring the Miniſtry into Bondage, they did not think it enough to wreſtle againſt it by Perſonal witneſſings; but by the good Hand of GOD upon their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, never ceaſed until it was condemned by Acts of <hi>Aſſembly.</hi> They proceeded alſo with great earneſtneſs and vigilance, to purge the Church of corrupt and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Miniſters; ſadly regrateing afterwards, when they ſaw the effects of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of ſome of that Character in the Miniſtrie, that they had not done more in that purging work. But now, after all the Rubbiſh and Filth, brought into the Houſe of GOD, by the Invaſions and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations of the Enemies, and Defections of Friends, when now Opportunity and Capacity is given to Rebuild and Beautifie the Houſe of the LORD, and to Repair the Deſolations thereof, the preſent buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is ſo far advanced, without pulling down and purging away the Rubbiſh, and condemning theſe corruptions and defections, in complyance with them, or confeſſing and forſaking them, as our Fathers uſed to do: Now theſe courſes have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> rather left us, than we have foreſaken; And the Lords returning in Providence, without our returning to Him by Repentance, hath made any Reformation yet attained, while theſe Defections are neither confeſſed in humiliations, nor condemned in Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catories. And the <hi>Prelatical Clergy,</hi> after all the evil they have done, and bitter fruits they have produced, are yet kept in many places, and like to continue as a Seminary and Nurſerie of a corrupt Miniſtrie. As long as all this Rubbiſh ſtands, there can be little hope, either of Purity or Stability in the Superſtructure. In for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Reformations alſo, the Advancement uſed to be Progreſſive, beginning where the former Reformation ſtopt, and going forward, after they had got removed, what obſtructed it. But now the motion is Retrograde, going as far back, as that in <hi>1592.</hi> miſſing many Excellent ſteps of Reformation, attained after that to <hi>1649.</hi> In for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Reformations, our worthy Anceſtors uſed to begin with Renovation of the <hi>National Covenants,</hi> &amp; <hi>Acknowledgements</hi> of the <hi>Breaches</hi> thereof, which hitherto hath been neglected, to the great grief of many. It is alſo matter of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation to reflect, that in former Reformations, tho the Adverſaries troubled the Builders, and hired Counſellors againſt them, to fruſtrate their purpoſe, yet being Furniſhed and Spirited of the Lord, for that Generation work, they never ſtudied to pleaſe men, but to acquit themſelves as faithful Servants of their Princely Maſter Jeſus Chriſt, in witneſſing againſt all Sins and Corruptions of great and ſmall, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially; and in Acts of <hi>Aſſembly</hi> ordaining and recommending to all Miniſters,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153033:14"/>this faithfulneſs in applying their Doctrine to the Sins of the time, under pain of Cenſure. But now thô there was never greater freedom and encouragement for, and neceſſitie of faithfulneſs, when the Adverſaries of <hi>Judah</hi> are ſeeking to Build, but on deſign to marr the Work, and many are too much inclining to joyn in affinity with the People of theſe abominations: Yet it is ſadly wanting, and much Deſiderated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many Miniſters, who being long accaſtomed to fears, and conſtrained ſilence, under former hazards and tentations, have not yet recovered their Confidence and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, to cry a loud againſt, and not ſpare the iniquities of the time. We deſire alſo to joyne in that common regrate, that thô informer Reformations, this Church was not only for Order and Authority, beautiful as <hi>Tirzah,</hi> comely as <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and terrible as an army with banners, but for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, got the Name of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> being then as much admired for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitie (which is the fruit of <hi>Presbyterian Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> wherever it hath place) as for any other Priviledge, which rendered her the Envy of all the Nations about. Yet now alas! The Crown hath fallen from our heads, wo unto us, that we have ſinned. This Holy and Beautiful Fabrick, hath been burnt up, with the fire of Enemies fury, with the fire of our Diviſions, and with the fire of the Lords indignation, burning againſt us for our defections, whereby the Lord was provoked to forſake his Houſe, and ſince his departure, there hath been nothing but disorder among his Children and Servants. The <hi>Popiſh Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latical</hi> and <hi>Malignant</hi> Party, have come in by Force and Fraud, and by the Cedings of thoſe, that ſhould have ſtood in the Gap, and broke down the Carved Work of our <hi>Covenanted Reformation,</hi> as with Axes and Hammers, Reſcinding all the Legal Bul-warks of Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitutions, Civil Sanctions, and <hi>National Covenants,</hi> wherewith it was fenced, Wherein alas! They were too much encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our faint reſiſtance, and too univerſal involvement in the ſin of ſubmitting to &amp; Countenancing of the intruſions of the <hi>Prelatical</hi> Party. At length having ſet up theſe their Enſignes for Signs, in Sign of compleate Victory, obtained over the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and Subjects of our exalted Prince, after they have invaded His Kingdom and Palace, and made Havock and Sloughter of ſuch, as would not yield, they offered ſome tempting terms, whereupon they would ſuffer them to live in ſubjection to theſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations; painted indeed with pretences of Favours, but really, at leaſt indirectly requiring a recognizance of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers power, and a Ceſſation from oppoſing the peaceable poſſeſſion of their Robberies. Theſe and the like defections on the one hand, together with many Extravagances on the other, have brought the Godly into many confuſions, ſtumbled them into many tontations, racked, rent, and almoſt ruined them with many Diviſions, promoted too much an every hand, by Paſſion, Pride, Prejudice, Jealouſie, too credulous and ſedulous taking up and ſpreading re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, and reproaches one of another, whereby the Spirit of GOD hath been grieved; the Power, Practice, and Spiritual Exerciſe of Religion obſtructed, the Goſpels ſucceſs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153033:14"/>marred, the Miniſtrie and all Ordinances brought into contempt, ungodlineſs encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, the mouths of the ungodly opened, their hearts hardned, and their hands ſtrengthned againſt us. And as the effect of all theſe, we may lament another ſad and very ſenſible want, the Lords Power and Glory not ſeen in the Sanctuary, as ſometimes in the former Houſe it was, with a ſpeciality of brightneſs; And the Spirit of Grace and Supplication, Repentance, and Reformation, publick Zeal for the Intereſt of Chriſt, and the Goſpel Spirit of Love and Tendernsſs towards Brethren, is not yet poured from on high. But it may be, if the Tabernacle were once reared up, that the cloud of the LORDS Preſence would cover it, and the Glorie of the LORD would fill it: And if we were aſhamed of our iniquities, we might then meaſure the Pattern, and ſee the form of the Houſe, and the faſhion thereof, and the goings out thereof, and the comings in thereof, and all the Ordinances thereof, and the whole limit thereof ſhould be holy, which is the Law of the Houſe: Then the glorie of this latter Houſe ſhould be greater than of the former.</p>
                  <p>Nevertheleſs, We are ſo far from deſpiſing the day of ſmall things, that in weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and humilitie, we would deſire to ſay, it is our higheſt ambition to enjoy the Communion of this Sanctuary of the LORD, in this Land, if it were but to be Door<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers in the Houſe of our GOD: And it is the matter of our greateſt longing to ſee the day, when all the Diſſintient and long Diſſevered Children of Zion, ſhal together with one heart take their Mother by the Hand; and with one Lip praiſe their Father, in the Beautie of Holineſs. For when the Courts of the LORD are amiable in Order, it cannot but be pleaſant and deſireable for Brethren to dwell together in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitie; And ſo much the more, that we have felt the ſad effects of our unhappie Diviſions, which not onlie now, but even in their greateſt heat, made us with much longing, deſire and pray for a comfortable <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, and to bemoan the Cauſes and Effects of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes of it; upon all occaſions declaring our dread and deteſtation of Schiſm, as a very heinious, hurtful and hateful ſin. We did indeed demure to concure with and follow, and did think it our dutie, <hi>pro tempore,</hi> to withdraw from theſe Miniſters (thô ſtill we owned and eſteemed them as godlie Miniſters of this Church) who promoted courſes of defection after ſpecified; and to adhere to thoſe (thô but few) who were more ſtedfaſt and faithful, in that time of Diviſions, Gonfuſions, and abounding ſnares, when the Church was in a broken ſtate, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of the Remedie of Church Judicatories, whereunto we might recurr with Complaints and Supplications, for removing theſe Offences: And when the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ſo <hi>Tyrannical,</hi> that if there had been Church Judicatories, neither durſt, they have correſponded with us, nor we make Application to them, for hazard of our Lives. When alſo the caſe was ſo ſtated, that we thought communion could not be kept by us with them, from whom we withdrew without ſin, while the very exerciſe of their Miniſtrie, in the then circumſtances, was ſo far depending upon, ſubordinate unto, complying with, modified and authoriſed by, <hi>unlawful Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:153033:15"/>that our joining would have inferred, at leaſt in our conſcience, a ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to, ſymbolizing with, and approving of their offenſive yieldings, to theſe encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Yet we never thought this a <hi>Schiſm;</hi> We never judged it, to be a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> either in Her Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline, or Government, as it ſtood Reformed and Covenanted to be preſerved; Nor did we gather, or ſet up formed ſeparate Churches or Societies, under another Government or Miniſtrie, diſtinct from, and independent upon the <hi>Presbyterial Church of Scotland;</hi> nor did we ever maintain, but alwayes abhorred that <hi>Sectarian</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the Perſonal Sins and Scandalls of Fellow-worſhippers, Miniſters or Profeſſors, did pollute the Ordinances; nor did we ever owne, but alwayes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned, a poſitive or active, total or ſtated Separation, from all the Miniſtry, or from any, for any Offence, in any caſe, where either the Offence could be then legally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, or was in it ſelf a thing to be condeſcended upon, or forborn, or did not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard our Involvement in the ſin of it: And only for the time, owned a Negative, Paſſive, and Conditional Abſtraction from ſome, refuſing to follow the Backſliding part of the Miniſtry, in their courſes of Defection, and chooſing to abide by that Part that perſevered in their Integrity. But now that <hi>Tyranny,</hi> that chaſed us from one another, being through Mercy removed, and theſe Snares and Stumbling-blocks, which ſcared us, from Communion with many, being ſo far taken out of the way, that they ceaſe to be Tentations involving us in ſin, and bones of Contention engaging us in continual janglings about them: Church Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catories being now in capacity, to give ſome remedy to theſe Evils, ſince Providence alſo hath ſo far altered the caſe, and matter of our Contendings, for the Faith de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Saints, that it calls all diſſentient Parties, among <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> to concenter in one common Teſtimony, for the common Reformation, againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Adverſaries. We hope this much deſired and long looked for <hi>Union,</hi> is, and ſhall be more acceſsable and attainable: Therefore, to the end, that this happy and deſireable <hi>Union,</hi> may be Holy and Comfortable, in a way that may procure, and ſecure our <hi>Union</hi> and <hi>Communion</hi> with the LORD: And as the famous <hi>Voe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> ſayes, <hi>Ut nihil de veritate &amp; profeſſione noſtra remittamus at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad eo à perfectione ad quam cum DEO pervenimus non relabamur ad im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectionem.</hi> Conſidering in all the Periods of this Church, from her firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, a Witneſs hath never been wanting, againſt the ſame, or equivalent Corruptions, that have offended us: And no method can be more adapted, for recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and reſtoring <hi>Union,</hi> than that which was uſed, for preſerving it: And that hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aimed hitherto, to offer &amp; keep up our Mite of a <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> thô weak &amp; inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, againſt the ſame; if now under the convictions of its remaining righteouſneſs, we ſhall paſs from it, &amp; ſo ſeem to condemn what we approved before, &amp; approve what we condemned before, it will leave an indeleble reproach, not only on our ſelves, but on our Contendings and Sufferings. Becauſe likewiſe in a Conference with ſome Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153033:15"/>Brethren, and Members of this <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> about theſe things it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and conceded, as an expedient, for eaſing our Conſciences, that we ſhould have liberty to remonſtrate and repreſent, to the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> what was offenſive to us. We earneſtly deſire, Right Reverend, you would be pleaſed to condeſcend to us, in ſome things, that we humbly conceive, are very needful, juſt to be ſought, and eaſie to be granted. We know and are confident, your Zeal for Truth and Peace, will ſuggeſt the ſame means and meaſures, for obtaining this end, and will urge you to take notice of the ſame things, we deſire without our advertiſement: Nor do we take upon us to preſeribe the Methods, Terms or Conditions, neceſſary for Compoſing theſe unhappy Differences, and reſtoring the holy and happy <hi>Union</hi> in the Lord; But we think, the Word and Works of God this day, points at theſe, which we crave leave in the Bowels of Chriſt, to remonſtrate unto your ſerious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</p>
                  <p>That to the end the cauſes of our <hi>Diviſions,</hi> the Anger of the Lord, as the Holy Cauſe, and our Mutual offences, as the ſinful Cauſe, May be removed, that the effect may ceaſe, a Mutual, impartial, and accurate ſearch and trial may be made into our wayes, to find out, and remember from whence we are fallen, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover our manifold and manifeſt defections, from the right wayes of the Lord; That the great wrongs and indignities done to our Great Head and King, by Enemies En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments on his Prerogatives, and his Kingdoms Liberties, and our Comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances therewith, on the one hand and one the other, may not be paſt in oblivion, but diligently inquired into, and what acceſſion to them, or Participation with them, all of us have been involved in, theſe <hi>30.</hi> years bygone: Particularly that it be laid to Heart, what Indignity to the Lord Jeſus, and Injury to his Church, was done by the introduction of abjured, <hi>Dioceſan</hi> and <hi>Eraſtian Prelacy,</hi> and the ſeveral de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Complyance therewith; As Miniſters leaving their Paſtoral Charge, at the Command of the Magiſtrate, and laying aſide the Exerciſe of their Miniſtrie, giving way unto, and not teſtifying againſt the Intruſions of <hi>Prelatick Curats;</hi> Particularly owning &amp; ſubmitting to their Miniſtry, &amp; receiving ordinances diſpenſed by them, and by Counſel and Example, Encouraging others to do the like: Which we cannot but <hi>Plead</hi> and <hi>Proteſt</hi> againſt as ſinful and Scandalous. <hi>1.</hi> Becauſe they were, and are inanifeſt Intruders, not entering in at the door, in the way and order of Chriſt, not having, yea deſpiſing and renouncing a Call from the People, and Ordination by the Presbytrie, and having no other external Call, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority or Right to officiate in this Church, as its proper Paſtors, but the <hi>Collation</hi> of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Preſentation</hi> of <hi>Patrons,</hi> who are none of Chriſts Officers, and forefaulting and foregoing any other Right, that any of them formerly could pretend to, by palpable defection to the Enemies of this Church. <hi>2.</hi> Becauſe both in Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and Profeſſion, and in the way af their Entry unto their Paſtoral Charge, they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153033:16"/>were, and are <hi>Eraſtians,</hi> deriving their Power from, and ſubjecting it in its exerciſe to another Head then Chriſt, the Magiſtrats <hi>Supremacy</hi> by which only they were Authorized, without Chriſts warrant, or the Churches conſent. <hi>3.</hi> Becauſe they were, and are <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> who cauſed Diviſions and Offences, contrary to the Doctrine of this Church, breaking her <hi>Union</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> going out themſelves from the fellowſhip of this Church, and leading People away from her vowed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; yea who violently thruſt out, and perſecuted her faithful Paſtors and Children, for adhering to that Reformation, which they deſigned to raze and ruine. <hi>4.</hi> Becauſe they were, and are perjured <hi>Covenant breakers,</hi> avowedly diſown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our <hi>Covenants,</hi> and ſtated in oppoſition to that Reformation, which is therein ſworn to be maintained. <hi>5.</hi> Becauſe they were, &amp; are in ſeveral Points <hi>Erroneous,</hi> in their Doctrine, many of them tainted with the Leaven of <hi>Popery, Arminianiſm,</hi> and <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> &amp; all of them Heteradox, in the point of the Magiſtrates power in Church matters, in the matter of Oaths, and in condemning the Work of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and Covenants; ſeducing thereby their Hearers, and both poſitively by theſe Doctrines, &amp; privatively by withholding other neceſſary Inſtructions, and Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Murdering their Souls. <hi>6.</hi> Becauſe they were, and are upon all theſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts <hi>Scandalous,</hi> and the Objects of the Churches Cenſure: And thô through the iniquity of the times, their deſerved Cenſure, hitherto hath not been inflicted, yet they ſtand upon the matter convict, by clear Scripture Grounds, and by the ſtanding Acts, and judicial Deciſion of this Church, in her Supreme Judicatories. <hi>7.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this hearing and ſumitting to them, was required as a <hi>Badge, Teſt,</hi> and <hi>Evidence</hi> of Due Acknowledgement of, and hearty Compylance with <hi>Eraſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm</hi> and <hi>Prelacy,</hi> or His Majeſties Government Eccleſiaſtick, <hi>Act. Parl. 1. Char. 2. July 10. 1663.</hi> which made it a caſe of Confeſſion to withſtand it. <hi>8.</hi> Becauſe by our Covenants, we are obliged to ſtand at a diſtance, from ſuch courſes of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and to extirpate them; yet in contradiction hereunto, we were commanded by the Reſcinders of the Covenants, to bear the <hi>Prelatick Curats,</hi> as a Badge of our yeilding to the reſcinding of the Govenants. <hi>9.</hi> Becauſe this Courſe was <hi>Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive</hi> and <hi>Stumbling,</hi> both in hardening thoſe that complyed with <hi>Prelacy,</hi> and weakening the Hands of thoſe that oppoſed it, and inferred a condemning of their Sufferings upon this Head. Eſpecially, <hi>10.</hi> When <hi>Communion</hi> with them was ſo ſtated, that therein was not only a <hi>Caſe of Controverſie</hi> among the Godly, in which alwayes Abſtinence is the ſureſt ſide, nor only in the judgement of many a <hi>Caſe of Confeſſion,</hi> which is alwayes dangerous to contradict and condemn, but undeny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably a <hi>Caſe of Competition,</hi> between the true Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> her Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Profeſſors, owning and adhering to her Holy Eſtabliſhments, claiming a Divine Right to their Offices and Priviledges, contending for the Churches Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; and a Schiſmatical Party, ſetting up a new Church, in a new Order, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153033:16"/>a new Head, robbing them of their Offices and Priviledges, and overturning the Reformation.</p>
                  <p>We muſt preſume to <hi>Plead</hi> alſo, That Enquiry be made unto the Heinous and Heaven-daring Affront, done to the Holineſs of GOD, in the horrid Violations of our Holy <hi>Covenants, National and Solemn League,</hi> not only how the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh, Prelatical,</hi> and <hi>Malignant</hi> Party, have broken them, enacted the Breaches of them, by Law, Burnt them, and endeavoured to Bury them, by making it a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital Crime to owne their Obligation, and by bringing in and ſubſtituting in their room, Conſcience enſnaring <hi>Anti-covenants, Oaths, Bonds,</hi> and <hi>Engagements</hi> renouncing the former, and obliging to Courſes contradictory thereunto: But that it may be conſidered, how many wayes, Miniſters and Profeſſors, in this time of tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and tribulation, have been guilty of breach of theſe holy Covenants: particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by conſenting unto, ſubſcribing, ſwearing, and taking any of the new multiplied, miſchievouſly contrived, captiouſly conceived, and Tyrannically impoſed <hi>Oaths, Teſts,</hi> or <hi>Bonds,</hi> in matters of Religion, ſince the overturning of the Covenanted Reformation, and eſtabliſhment of Prelacy; and by perſwading People to take them, and forbearing a neceſſary warning of the danger of them, and leaving People in the dark, to determine themſelves, in the midſt of theſe ſnares. All which we <hi>Plead</hi> and <hi>Proteſt,</hi> againſt as ſinful and ſcandalous. <hi>(1)</hi> Becauſe all of them, did infer, import, and imply a ſinful unitive conjunction, Incorporation, Aſſociation, and Confederacy, with the People of theſe Abominations, that were promoting a courſe of Apoſtaſie from GOD. <hi>(2)</hi> Becauſe all of them were incapable of the Qualifications, required in Sacred Engagements, to be taken in Truth, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and Judgement. <hi>(3)</hi> Becauſe all of them, in the ſenſe of the Impoſers, interpreted by their Acts and Actings, were condemnatory of, and contradictory unto the Covenants, &amp; ſome part of the Covenanted Reformation. <hi>(4)</hi> Becauſe by the Ancient Acts of Aſſembly, all publick Oaths impoſed by the Malignant Party, without conſent of the Church are condemned. <hi>July 28. 1648. Ante merid. Seſſ. 18.</hi> And</p>
                  <q>Thoſe Miniſters are Ordained to be Cenſured, who ſubſcribe any Bonds, or take any Oaths, not approven by the <hi>General Aſſembly,</hi> or by their Counſel, Countenance, or Approbation, make themſelves acceſſary to the taking of ſuch Bonds and Oaths.</q>
                  <p>In like manner we dare not forbear to <hi>Cry</hi> and <hi>Crave,</hi> that it may be conſidered, what wrongs Chriſt hath received from the <hi>Eraſtian</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation</hi> of the <hi>Supremacy,</hi> encroaching upon the Prerogative of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt his incommunicable Headſhip and Kingship, as Mediator, giving to a Man, a Magiſterial, and Architectonick power, to alter and innovate, Authoriſe and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auctorate, allow or reſtrain, and diſpoſe of the Government and Governours of the Church, according to his pleaſure; invading the liberties of the Goſpel Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153033:17"/>a civil Dominion upon her Government, contrare to its nature, being only a Miniſterial-Stewardſhip, diſtinct from the Civil Government, in its Nature, Cauſes, Ends, Officers, and Actings, and giving to the Magiſtrate the power of the keyes, without and againſt Chriſts Donation and Authority, even the Dogmatick, Critick, and Diatactick, Deciſive Suffrage, and Power, in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtick, which Chriſt hath intruſted to the Church Repreſentatives; and denying to the Church, the Exerciſe of theſe Keyes and Powers, without the Magiſtrates warrand and Indulgence. We crave alſo, that it may be inquired into, how far this encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hath been connived at, ſubmitted unto, complyed with, homologate, ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and eſtabliſhed, by receiving and accepting, without conſent of the Church, yea againſt the expreſs diſsent, and teſtimony of ſome faithfull Miniſters, to the contrare, the <hi>Indulgences, anno 1669,</hi> and <hi>1679:</hi> And by the ſilence of others, not witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing againſt the ſame, and others cenſuring the Faithful, for diſcovering the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs thereof. Which we <hi>Remonſtrate</hi> upon theſe grounds complexly conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>(1)</hi> Becauſe as the contrivance and end of the grant thereof, was to advance and eſtabliſh the <hi>Supremacy;</hi> to engage <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> either to co-operate to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſettling and ſtrengthening thereof, or to ſurceaſe from oppoſing the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able poſſeſſion of the Granters <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation, and to extort from them, at leaſt an indirect Recognizance, of acknowledged Subordination in Miniſterial Exerciſes, to his uſurped power, in a way which would he beſt acquieſced in; To ſuppreſs the Preaching and Propagation of the Goſpel in perſecuted Meetins in houſes and fields, ſo neceſſary at that time; and to divide and increaſe differences and animoſities among Presbyterians, by inſinuating upon theſe called the more <hi>Moderate,</hi> to commend the <hi>Indulger</hi> his Clemency, while other <hi>Non-Conformiſts,</hi> adhering to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted duties, were juſtly complaining of the Effects of his Severity. And as the woful effects of it, ſtrengthening the Supremacy, weakening the hands of theſe that witneſſed againſt it, extinguiſhing Zeal, and increaſing many diviſions, did cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpond with theſe wretched deſigns; So theſe could not be counteracted, but very much ſtrengthened and promotted, by the Acceptance of the <hi>Indulgence,</hi> which in its own nature, was ſo palpably ſubſervient thereto, even thô there had been a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie againſt theſe deſigns and ends, yet when the means adapted to theſe ends, were complied with, it was rendered irrite and <hi>contra factam. (2)</hi> Becauſe as the Supremacie received much Strength and Increment from the <hi>Indulgence,</hi> ſo reciprocally it had its Riſe, Spring, Conveyance, and ſubſiſtence from the Supremacy; from which it flowed, upon which it ſtood, and by which at length it was removed: And in the grant and conveyance of the <hi>Indulgence,</hi> all the power of the Supremacy, was arrogate, aſſerted and exerted, in firſt taking away the power of the Keyes, from CHRISTS Stewards, and then reſtoring only one of them, to ſome few, with Reſtrictions bounding, and Inſtructions
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153033:17"/>regulating them in the exerciſe of that. The Acceptance whereof, ſo clogged with theſe complex Circumſtances, without a clear &amp; diſtinct Teſtimony, in that caſe of confeſſion, hath at leaſt a great appearance (which ſhould have been abſtained from) of a conniving at, ſubmitting unto, complying with, and homologating of that <hi>Eraſtian</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation. <hi>(3)</hi> Becauſe, as it was interpreted to be accepted in the ſame Terms, wherein it was granted, without a Teſtimony againſt the Supremacy, ſo the Entry of thoſe Miniſters to their Churches, by this <hi>Indulgence,</hi> was prejudicial to the Churches Priviledge: Some of them being fixed in particular Churches, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they had no peculiar Paſtoral Relation before, and ſome tranſplanted from one Church to another, without the interpoſure of any Eccleſiaſtick Presbyterial Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, without the free and orderly Call of the People, being in many reſpects preli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, and in the way of <hi>Patronages,</hi> at the <hi>Councils</hi> Pleaſure and Order; and thoſe that were Reſtored to their own Churches, being there admitted, not by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of their Old Right, and claim of an undiſſolved Relation, but by vertue of a New Holding on the <hi>Indulgence. (4)</hi> Becauſe the embracing thereof, and the continuing therein, was a faint yielding to prevailing <hi>Eraſtianiſm,</hi> &amp; a courſe of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from former Integrity of Miniſterial Freedom and Faithfulneſs, in which the Servants and Witneſſes of Jeſus Chriſt, were Famous and Eminent in former times, who for writing, Preaching, and proteſting againſt the <hi>Eccleſiaſtick Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy,</hi> in the Magiſtrate, and all <hi>Eraſtian</hi> courſes, did bear the croſs of Chriſt, with much ſtedfaſtneſs; Yea a receding from, and foregoing of a very matterial part of the Cauſe and Teſtimonie of the <hi>Church of Scotland,</hi> which till then, did conſtantlie wreſtle againſt ſuch encroachments: And in this reſpect <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> becauſe hardening to <hi>Eraſtian</hi> Enemies, ſtumbling to many Friends, and offenſive to Poſteritie. <hi>(5)</hi> Becauſe it is contradictorie to our <hi>Covenants,</hi> to receive <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences,</hi> contrived and conferred on purpoſe, to divide (by the terror of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution on the one hand, and the perſwaſion of this pretended Libertie, taking off the Legal reſtraint on the other) Miniſters &amp; People from the Cauſe and Teſtimony of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> againſt the <hi>Supremacy,</hi> &amp; from their former bleſſed Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction therein, and to induce them to make Defection to that Party, that were Advanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Eraſtianiſm.</hi> And it is expreſly contradictory to the <hi>Engagement to Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> Anno <hi>1649,</hi> where the Obligation bears, <q rend="inline">Becauſe many have of late labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to ſupplant the Liberties of the Kirk, we ſhall Maintain and Defend the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in all her Liberties and Priviledges, againſt all who ſhall oppoſe or undermine the ſame, or encroach thereupon under any pretext whatſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Likewiſe, we <hi>Plead</hi> and <hi>Obteſt,</hi> that a Search may be made, into, and a review taken of the late <hi>Toleration,</hi> the <hi>Addreſſing</hi> for it, and <hi>Acceptance</hi> of it, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexely conſidered: The ſinfulneſs whereof, we could not, and now cannot forbear
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153033:18"/>to <hi>Witneſs</hi> againſt. <hi>(1)</hi> Becauſe as the Deſign of the <hi>Granter,</hi> and Tendency of the <hi>Grant</hi> it ſelf, in its own nature, being the Introduction of Popery and Slavery, could not in any probability be counteracted, but rather corroborated, by this Addreſſing for it, and Accepting of it, even thô there had been a Teſtimony againſt the deſign there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as there was none, and could be none conſiſtent with the continuance thereof; ſo being conveyed from <hi>Abſolute Power,</hi> which all were required <hi>to obey with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſerve,</hi> Stopping, Suſpending, and Diſabling all the <hi>Penal Statutes,</hi> againſt <hi>Papiſts,</hi> thereby undermining all the Legal Bulwarks of our Religion: The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing for, and Accepting of it, ſo conveyed, without a witneſs againſt this Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potical Encroachment (yea the very condition of enjoying the benefit of it, being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſive of ſuch a Teſtimony, which might any way tend, to the alienating of the People from ſuch a deſpotical Government, in all its Encroachments) did indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, at leaſt, imply Complyance with, if not the Recognizance and Acknowledgement of that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped Power, and the Arbitrary Exerciſe and Effect of it in ſuſpending the <hi>Penal Statutes. (2)</hi> Becauſe it was extended, not only to <hi>Prelacy,</hi> but to <hi>Popery, Quakeriſm,</hi> and all Idolatry, Blaſphemie, and Hereſie, which was highly provoking to the Lord Jeſus, and prejudical to the Peace and Purity of His Church; contrary to the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament; contrary to our Confeſſion of Faith and Gatechiſms, <hi>Chap. 20. §. 4.</hi> and <hi>Chap. 23. §. 3.</hi> Being placed alſo among the ſins of the ſecond Command, in the Larger Catechiſm; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trare to the Principles of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> being condemned, warned of, and witneſſed againſt, by <hi>Acts of Aſſembly, anno 1649.</hi> And by her faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Paſtors Preaching, Writing, and Proteſting againſt ſuch <hi>Tolerations,</hi> (and ſometimes, even when <hi>Papiſts</hi> were exccluded, as that, againſt which the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Fife</hi> and <hi>Perth</hi> did teſtifie) And contrary to our <hi>Covenants,</hi> wherein we are bound to preſerve Reformation and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and Government, to extirpate <hi>Popery,</hi> &amp;c. to free our Souls from the guilt of other Mens Sins, defend our Liberties, and conſequently never to comply with a <hi>Toleration,</hi> everſive of all theſe Intereſts we are ſworn to maintain, and intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductive of theſe things, we are ſworn to endeavour the Extirpation of. <hi>(3)</hi> Becauſe it was clogged with ſuch Conditions and Limitations, as did exceedingly hamper the Freedom of the Miniſtry, being Offered (in <hi>Proclamations</hi>) and Accepted (in <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes</hi> and <hi>Obedeince</hi>) with Reſtrictions to Perſons, who might Preach, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſome, and diſcharging others, who had as good Authority, as they, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe their Miniſtry) To Places where they ſhould preach (only where Intimation was given of the Name of the Place, and of the Preacher, to ſome of the Lords of the <hi>Council,</hi> &amp;c.) And to the matter What, or at leaſt what they might not preach, to wit, nothing that might have any tendency, to alienate the Hearts of the People from a Popiſh and Tyranical Government, and conſequently nothing againſt the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153033:18"/>wickedneſs, or of the Miſery of Tyranny; nothing againſt the <hi>Toleration,</hi> and the open Sins proclaimed therein, and wicked Ends deſigned thereby; nothing againſt diſabling the <hi>Penal Statutes,</hi> or for the Obligation of them, and Ties of National Covenants ſtrengthning them <hi>(4)</hi> Becauſe of the manifold <hi>Scandal</hi> of it, we cannot but witneſs againſt it, being ſo diſgraceful to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion, and prejudicial to the Intereſt thereof. It was reproachful to our Religion, ſometimes eſtabliſhed by Law, then only Tolerate, under the Notion of an Evil to be ſuffered; How Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding and Conſternating was this, to all the Reformed Churches, that ſometimes admired and envied <hi>Scotlands</hi> Eſtabliſhments, now to ſee her ſo diſpirited and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, as to Accept and Addreſs for a <hi>Toleration,</hi> without a Teſtimony, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by inſtead of all the Laws and Covenants ſecuring her Reformation, the only Tenure and Security for it, ſhe had now remaining, was, the Arbitrary Word of an Abſolute Prince, whoſe Principles obliged him to break it? What occaſion of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainful Inſulting, did it give to the <hi>Prelatical</hi> Party, then Pleading for the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Laws, to obſerve <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> acquieſcing in that which ſuſpended and ſtopped the <hi>Penal Statutes?</hi> Yea, what matter of Gloriation, and Boaſting was it to <hi>Papiſts,</hi> to ſee <hi>Presbyterians</hi> ſleeping and ſuccumbing, and not oppoſing, when at this opened Gap, they were bringing in the <hi>Trojan</hi> Horſe of <hi>Poperty</hi> and <hi>Slavery?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Moreover with reſpect to ſome things at preſent, which we account Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and are offenſive to many, we cannot forbear to <hi>Remonſtrate</hi> and <hi>Plead,</hi> that Conſideration may be taken, of the ſinfulneſs of the too univerſal Defect and Neglect, of Zeal and Faithfulneſs, in reviving the buried <hi>National Covenants,</hi> when now they ſeem to be laid aſide, and many Miniſters, forbear to Preach plainly the obligation of them, and diſcover particularly, the Breaches of them, and to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion them in Engagements, which they require of Parents, when they preſent their Children to Baptiſme, according to the continved Cuſtom of faithful Miniſters, theſe many years bygone: And it is ſtumbling to many, that in all <hi>Addreſſes</hi> to King and Parliament, the Renewing of them hath not been deſired. This we think very grievous <hi>(1)</hi> Becauſe in the Scriptures, as we have many Precepts, Promiſes, and Precedents for Renewing them, and Demonſtrations of their Perpetual, indiſſoluble obligation being in their matter and forme aggreable with the Word of God; So we have many Denunciations and Certifications of unavoidable threatnings of all evils, National, Perſonal, Temporal, Spiritual, and Eternal, againſt forſaking or forgetting them. <hi>(2)</hi> Becauſe as there is no other way to prevent the Curſe of the Covenants, and this threatned wrath iminent upon the Land, for breach of Covenants, but to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the breaches of them, and engage again to the Duties of them; So theſe omiſſions, cannot conſiſt with that faithfulneſs, required of Miniſters in ſuch a Caſe. <hi>(3)</hi> Becauſe it is a plain defection from firſt love, and former Attainments of our Fathers, who
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:153033:19"/>commenced all Reformations, with Renovations of the Covenants: And in their Eccleſiaſtick Conſtitutions, enjoyned to all Miniſters, to Preach up the Covenants, &amp; Witneſs againſt all defections from them, and indifferency or Luke-warmneſs in them, which alſo is a breach of Covenant in it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>Hence more Particularly, we cannot but ſiguify how much, we and many others are offended, at the too general keeping ſilenee at, or very ambigvous ſpeaking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and omitting the plain and Impartial Doctrinal Rebuking of ſuch Crying ſins and ſcandalls of the times, as cannot be Controverted among <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> Such as the impoſſing and taking many <hi>Bonds</hi> and <hi>Oaths,</hi> repugnant to the Covenants and work of Reformation, which many Complied with to ſhift Perſecution, and many others to Purchaſe preferments unto places of Truſt; The acceſſion of Nobles &amp; Rulers to the wicked eſtabliſhments and framing miſchiefs into Laws in former times; The manifold involvements of great and ſmall, in the guilt of Perſecution, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating and informing againſt honeſt ſuffering People, Riding with Armed Foree, to purſue and Apprehend them, appearing under diſplayed Banners for the defence of Tyranny, on Expeditions againſt them, at <hi>Pentland, Bothwel-Bridge, &amp;c.</hi> Sitting in Courts Juries and Aſſyſes, to condemn them, putting them out of Houſes &amp; Tenements under them, becauſe they would not Comply with ſinful impoſitions: And eſpecially the defyling of the Land with Blood, which hath yet a Cry in the Ears of the Lord God of Sabaoth: All which the Servants of the Lord, are obliged by the Word of God, and the Conſtitutions of this Church, to Cry againſt, and not to ſpare, and to reprove and rebuke in Seaſon and out of Seaſon.</p>
                  <p>Finally, we muſt preſume, to lay open our own, and the general Complaints, through ſeveral corners of the Land, of the ſad Slackneſs and Remiſneſs of <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline:</hi> The Report and <hi>Fama Clomoſa</hi> whereof, at leaſt doth wound our Ears, aad pierce our Hearts; To wit, That ſome who had gone a great length in the above-mentioned <hi>Complyances,</hi> even to the Swearing the <hi>Teſt</hi> it ſelf, beſides other wicked <hi>Oaths,</hi> and to the perſecuting of the Godly ſundry wayes, are admitted to the Sacrament of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> and to preſent their Children to <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> And that others, are admitted to the Charge of <hi>Elders,</hi> who had not only habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally complyed with <hi>Prelacy,</hi> and had born the Name of that Office under that Government, but had taken theſe ſcandalous forementioned <hi>Oaths;</hi> yea and that of late, ſome are admitted to the Miniſtry, that conſtantly followed <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and were trained up to be <hi>Curats,</hi> and were deeply involved in the foreſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyances, without due Trial of their paſt Converſation, and requiring of their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Profeſſion of Repentance, and Reſentment of theſe reſpective Scandals; whereby the Precious are not taken from the Vile, and a litle of that old Leaven, may quickly leaven the whole Lump, and Offenders are not like thereby to be gained to Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, but rather hardened in, and tempted to think litle of theſe deſtroying Sins.</p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:153033:19"/>
                  <p>We plead not here, that every one of the defects, or every degree of theſe offences, ſhould be in the caſe of this Epidemick Involvement, proceeded againſt by diſciplinary Cenſure, nor do we urge, that all chargable with theſe offences above taxed, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch as are in Controverſie, ſhould be either Perſonally rebuked in publick, or obliged publickly to confeſs their own degree of the guilt of them, thô it would give glory to God, and Comfort to the Church, and peace to their own Conſciences, for all to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs their offences, that have been moſt ſtumbling to the Godly, ſo far as from the Word of God, and known Principles of this Reformed Church, they may be convinced. Nor do we propoſe, that the condemnation of every one of theſe ſteps of defection, that are queſtioned, ſhould be ſo far ſtretched <hi>quoad momentum rei,</hi> as either to be ſtated by us, as a ground of Separation formerly, or now required as a neceſſary condition of Communion; Thô ſtill, we conceive the complication of them together, when they ſtood, was a ground that neceſſitated our withdrawing, from many in the then Circumſtances. We only deſire, they may be ſo far inquired into, that what guilt is in them, before the Lord, may be in ſome meaſure diſcovered, and the wrongs done to Chriſt thereby, may not be paſſed over in an Act of oblivion: But as the Right honourable the <hi>Eſtates</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> have found &amp; declared, theſe Acts, &amp; Actings of the <hi>Overturners</hi> of our Reformation; and the miſchiefs of <hi>Prelacy, Supremacy,</hi> &amp; <hi>Tyranny,</hi> eſtabliſhed by wicked Laws which were the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Fountains of all the Offenceſive Complyances abovementioned, to be Grievances againſt the Laws of the Land; So the Right Reverend, the Members of this Vener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> may find and declare, theſe wicked eſtabliſhments and Complyances Supporting them, and defections flowing therefrom, to be ſins againſt the Laws of Chriſt; And ſo far as they can find Iniquity in the foreſaid offences, may provide by Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick Conſtitutions, for the future, that the like Complyances, with the like Contrivances of uſurping Enemies, may never again be allowed, under pain of Church Cenſures, to prevent and peeclude all fears of diviſions, to be occaſioned by the like defections, in time coming. And as we offer and Promiſe, ſo far as we are, or may be convinced, to confeſs our offences, any manner of way, that Church Judicatories ſhall appoint; So, for the ſatisfaction of all concerned in the late Differences, and removal of Offenſes, given or taken, we deſire and expect, that ſuch Failings in the above ſpecified particulars, or others be laid to Heart, by all ſorts of Miniſters and Preachers, as they are convinced of, or after ſearch, may be diſcovered to them, by this <hi>Reverend Aſſembly:</hi> And that theſe, among the Sins of the Land, be ſet down in order, as cauſes of a publick Faſt, upon ſome week day, through all the Meetings of <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> within this Kingdom, and that the Sins of the People be intermixed among theſe Cauſes.</p>
                  <p>Further, As we humbly conceive, it would prove a very proper and promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing expedient, for promoving, preſerving and propagating Reformation, for ſettl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:153033:20"/>and keeping Order and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, for preventing and precluding innovations or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, for diſcovering and diſcouraging Apoſtates or Schiſmaticks, Malignants or Sectaries, and excluding them from acceſs to do further hurt; ſo we hope, we ſhall be approven and ſeconded by many in this <hi>Reverend Aſſembly,</hi> in craving the <hi>Renewing</hi> of the <hi>Covenants,</hi> either both the <hi>National,</hi> and <hi>Solemn League,</hi> with accommodations to our Times, or one made up of both, with Additions or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, ſuiting our preſent Caſe and Day, with a Solemn Acknowledgement of the publick Breaches, and Engagement to the Duties of the Covenants: Humbly moving, that none be forced to Swear or Subſcribe the ſame, or ſo much as admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to it, except they be ſuch, as may be judged in Charity, to have a competent knowledge, and ſenſe of the Sins and Duties thereof.</p>
                  <p>In Fine, thô we will not take upon us, to propoſe the time or the way, of purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the <hi>Epiſcopal Clergy,</hi> yet we cannot and dare not forbear, to <hi>Plead</hi> and <hi>Obteſt</hi> that they may not be continued, nor kept in the Churches, whereunto they have intruded, nor re-admitted that are, or may be laid aſide, until they give ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provable evidence of their Repentance, for their ſinful Conformity. <hi>(1)</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon all theſe Grounds, exhibited above, againſt hearing of them. <hi>(2)</hi> Becauſe, former experience of the hurt, received by the entertainment of the <hi>Epiſcopal Clergy,</hi> anno <hi>1638,</hi> does now plead for their care to prevent it in time coming. <hi>(3)</hi> Becauſe the People under their Miniſtry, have hitherto been, and are periſhing in Ignorance and Irreligion, being either ſtarved for want of Faithful and Spiritual Inſtruction, or poyſoned with falſe Inſtruction; and therefore Pity to them, and Zeal to propagate the Goſpel, ſhould prompt to all endeavours, to purge them out. <hi>(4)</hi> Becauſe, the Settlement, Purgation, and Plantation of the Church, will be exceedingly obſtructed, by the continuance of them, that unſettled it, corrupted it, and peſtered the Lords Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, with Plants not of His planting, and whoſe Leaven will be alwayes in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard to leaven the whole Lump. <hi>(5)</hi> Becauſe, all of them are among theſe, whom the Laws of Chriſt do oblige, the Conſtitutions of this Church do ordain, and the preſent Civil Sanctions, for eſtabliſhing Church Government do allow the Church Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative, to try and purge out, being all of them either <hi>inſufficient,</hi> or <hi>negligent,</hi> or <hi>erroneous,</hi> or <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> if theſe Characters may be applied, or interpreted, accord<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing to Scripture Rules, or as the Church hath extended them heretofore. We are content that none of the <hi>Curats,</hi> be put out, but the unſufficient &amp; Ignorant, if this be one part of the trial of their knowledge, to inquire not only unto their Gifts but their Graces, if ignorance of Converſion, Regeneration, Sanctification, and Communion with God; both as to the Doctrine of theſe Benefits, and as to their own Experience of them, ſo far as may be diſcovered by humane Judgement, be reputed unſufficiency; We are content, none by put away, but the negligent, if ſo be they that do not warn the Wicked of their deſtroying Sins, that feed themſelves and not the Flock, that do not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153033:20"/>ſtrengthen the Diſeaſed, nor heal the Sick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>— That omitt the preſſing of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Duties impartially on Perſons and Families, and the cenſuring of Scandals, without reſpect of Perſons, be comprehended in that Character: We are ſatisfied, none be removed but the Erroneous, if they be judged to be ſuch, who not only owne Points of <hi>Popery, Arminianiſm,</hi> and <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> but are unſound in their Explanation of the Kingly Office of Chriſt, of the Perfection of the Scriptures in the point of Church Officers and Government, in the matter of Oaths, &amp; of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates Power, and do maintain <hi>Eraſtianiſm,</hi> an exploded and abjured Error in this Church: And we ſeek no more but that all be removed who are Scandalous, and none but they, if Intruders, Covenant-breakers, perjured Subſcribers of Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> Schiſmaticks, and Perſecuters, be counted among the Scandalous.</p>
                  <p>It were perhaps, <hi>Right Reverend,</hi> more ſuitable for us, who make ſo mean a Figure, among either Preachers or Profeſſors, to lay our Hand on our Mouth, in ſubmiſſive ſilence, waiting what your own Wiſdom and Zeal will produce by the good Hand of GOD upon you, for our ſatisfaction: But conceiving a chief Let and Impediment of our deſired comfort of <hi>Union,</hi> to conſiſt in the want of opportunity, of laying open our Hearts to you, and longing with much impatience for it, we could not forbear any longer, giving you the trouble of hearing us, wherein we requeſt, for the favour of laying aſide all preconceived Prejudices, and begg ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your charitable conſtruction of our ingenuous Freedom, and deprecate your cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical ſcanning the Infirmities, that may be obivous therein. Some things are indeed extraordinary, which we here urge, but as extraordinary Exigences do force us, to move without a Precedent, ſo they furniſh you a Power, to make a Precedent for the like caſes, thereafter: We confeſs alſo, it may ſeem precipitant to preſs all theſe things ſo hard, &amp; ſo ſoon, in a bruckle time, before things be better ſettled; but we fear if new delayes be procured till all things be fully ſettled, that the obſerving of Wind and Clouds ſhall hinder both Sowing and Reaping-But if laying aſide the Plaiſters, wherewith the Wounds of our Backslidings have been ſlightly covered rather than cured, you put to your Hand to the healing of our Breaches, in condeſcending to theſe our humble Deſires, you ſhall win the Bleſſing of many Souls, rent, and racked with theſe Diviſions; You ſhall disburden the Land of many weights and woes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it is weary; you ſhall ſend to all the Neighbouring Churches a Pattern, tranſmit to the Poſterity an Example, and Erect to all Ages a Monument of ſelf-denying, Zeal and Wiſdom; a work to be paralelled with the Glories of former times. If herein our hopes ſhall fail us, we ſhall not know whether to wiſh, we had died with our Brethren, by the Enemies hand, and had never ſeen this Reviving in our Bondage, for it will be a death to us, and not a reviving, if there be not a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning together to the LORD, ſearching and trying and diſcovering the iniquities of our wayes. But however, we intend not to ſeparat from the Church, but to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153033:21"/>
                     <hi>Union</hi> and <hi>Communion,</hi> in Truth and Duty, with all the Miniſters and Members of this Church, that do, and in ſo far as they do follow the Inſtitutions of Chriſt, and to approve our ſelves, GOD aſſiſting, as much for Peace and Concord, as ever we were ſuſpected to be Men of diviſive Principles; hoping it ſhall appear, we are ſeeking where <hi>He feedeth, and where He makes His Flock to reſt at noon,</hi> and are not as ſuch who turn aſide by the flocks of his Companions, but going forth by the footſteps of the Flocks, beſides the Shepherds Tents: Yet with this <hi>proteſted Diſſent</hi> from, and <hi>Teſtimony</hi> againſt all the above mentioned cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, defections, and offenſive Courſes, which oblieged us to ſtand at a diſtance, in times of Deformation, that our preſent joyning, in theſe circumſtances, when theſe are removed, may not infer or be interpreted, an Approving of what we former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Condemned, and be free from all partaking in theſe Defections, by Conſent, Connivance, Complyance, or Communion therein. For which we bumbly Supplicate, That theſe our <hi>Humble Propoſals,</hi> may be Recorded in the Books of <hi>Aſſembly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Tho. Lining. Al. Sheilds. Will. Boyd.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Act of <hi>Aſſemblie</hi> hereanent (which the <hi>Reverend Miniſters</hi> that were appointed to draw it, were Pleaſed firſt to let us ſee, and upon our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting againſt ſome Expreſſions of the firſt Draught, did Condeſcend to amend it) is here annexed;</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="act">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>Edinburgh. <date>
                           <hi>25.</hi> Octob. <hi>1690.</hi> Ante Merid. Seſſ. <hi>9.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WHereas Mr. <hi>Thomas Lining,</hi> Mr. <hi>Allexander Sheilds,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Wil-Boyd,</hi> have preſented to this <hi>Aſſembly</hi> two Papers: One containing the expreſſions of their Purpoſe and Promiſe of being ſubject to the Authority of this Church, as formerly Conſtituted, and now Reſtored in its ſeveral Judicatories: The other offered for the exoneration of their Conſciences. Which Paper, containing their Submiſſion and Subjection, did after the exhibition of the other to the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> become binding upon them, according to the promiſe therein made. Like as after that other and longer Paper, had been read before the Committee of Overtures, it was exhibite to, and Received by the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> together with the Reaſons from the ſaid Committee, why it ſhould not be publickly read in full <hi>Aſſembly.</hi> Which Reaſons being duely conſidered; And the ſaid other Paper of Submiſſion and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection publickly Read, and Judicially owned by the forenamed Perſons in preſence of the <hi>Aſſembly.</hi> The <hi>Aſſembly</hi> did conclude by one ſingle Vote, that the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153033:21"/>longer Paper ſhould not be read; And that the above named Perſons ſhould be Received into the fellowſhip of this Church, on the terms of Submiſſion and Subjection contained in the ſaid Paper: And after paſſing of the ſaid Vote, and that they were gravely Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by the Moderator to walk Orderly in time coming, in oppoſition to all Schiſme &amp; Diviſion, it was Declared to them, by the <hi>Moderator,</hi> in the name of the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> that the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> did receive them into the Fellowſhip of this <hi>Church,</hi> to enjoy the Priviledges thereof, and perform the Duties therein, whereof they are, or ſhall be found Capable. Whereupon, and at their Deſire, it was Ordained, that the Act ſhould be made, and an Extract thereof given to them in good Forme. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted out of the Records of the</hi> Aſſembly.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>JO. SPALDING, Cls. Syn. Gen.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>From which <hi>Act,</hi> we ſhall only take notice of two things. One is, That our Paper of <hi>Propoſals</hi> was neither refuſed or rejected, but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Aſſembly; Nor was it canvaſſed or cognoſced upon; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe judged inconvenient to be Read; Nor was it condemned, without Cognizance or Deciſion, by the Character given of it in the Overtures, ſince it is plain the Vote of the Aſſembly was not, whether the Reaſons or Character given in the Overtures ſhould be approven or not, But it was concluded by one ſingle Vote only, <hi>That the foreſaid longer Paper ſhould not be Read, And that the abovenamed Perſons ſhould be Received,</hi> &amp;c. As the Act Declares, There is a great Difference betwixt the Voting that it ſhould not be Read, and Voting that it ſhould not be Read for theſe Reaſons of the Overtures. A ſecond is, That it appears we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the Communion of this Church, upon no Terms condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natory of, or contradictory unto our former Teſtimony; But only <hi>on the Terms of Submiſſion and Subjection contained in the Shorter Paper;</hi> Which ſhorter Paper did introduce our Teſtimony and oblieged us to Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Subjection after the Exhibition of it; And therefore the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion could not be contrary to it.</p>
            <p>But now to conclude, with a hint at our <hi>Motives,</hi> that induced us to this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> which may be as variouſly miſconſtructed and miſrepreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as our deſign was, in applying to the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> for it, and as the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and effect of that application was, the miſtakes whereof are touched above. We can with ſome ſingleneſs of Heart ſay, as far as Infirmity or Corruption may allow, that we were not induced to it, from any Carnal motive, or for any ſelfiſh end: It was not any lucrative proſpect of outward Profits or Emoluments in Settlements, or Anxiety for proviſion,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:153033:22"/>that prompted us to it: Neither was it the alluring Pleaſures of Peace and Eaſe, and the expectation of better Accomodations, then we could have in an unſetled Lot, or Impatience under the inconveniencies thereof, that perſuaded us to it: Nor was it the hope of airy honour and popular Applauſe which we had in greater meaſure, and with greater noiſe, as we ſtood before, and which we could not well expect by <hi>Svbmiſſion,</hi> but rather the contrare; Thô to get the honour of being <hi>Peaceable</hi> and <hi>Faithful,</hi> and the Bleſſing of <hi>Peace-makers,</hi> was truely the matter of our Ambition: Nor was it any provocation from, or diſſatisfaction with that part of the Lords People, with whom we had ſweet fellowſhip, that tempted us to joyn with theſe, from whom they and we, were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned before: Nor was it any Levity of Mind, Inconſtancy of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or change of Principles, that moved us to this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> and <hi>Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion:</hi> For thô there had been ſuch a change of Thoughts about theſe thornie Points, upon which our Differences and Diviſions were ſtated; yet as in that caſe, we, who require ſuch plainneſs of Confeſſion, in others, could not but think our ſelves obliged to declare ſuch a Change in ſome open Recantation, So it would not have been our ſhame to Confeſs our Errors. Our Sentiments are ſhallow, and changeable, as other Mens, having the imperfection of Mutability, as well as Fallibility, common to all, in this ſide of time; nevertheleſs it was not any change of Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but only change of providential Circumſtances, that made us now ſubmit, and not before. For as we adhere to our Teſtimony, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to the Venerable <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and to the ſubſtance of all our former Teſtimouies; ſo we know no Truth or Duty, that ever we aſſerted or contended for, but what we think, we could Seal with our Blood, if we were called to it: And we know no Corruption, Defection, or Sin, that ever we witneſſed againſt, or withdrew from, but what we would yet contend againſt, and withdraw from, in the ſame manner, if we were in the ſame Circumſtances, and yet think our ſelves obliged to contend and witneſs againſt, but not in a divided way, but in a way of <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> according to the Apoſtles way of the Spirits of the Prophets being ſubject to the Prophets.</p>
            <p>Our True and Sincere <hi>Motives</hi> then, inducing us to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> and <hi>Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> which in theſe Circumſtances, had ſuch force on our Conſciences, that we durſt not reſiſt for a World, were theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">I. It was ever our Judgement, that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> and <hi>Communion</hi> is neceſſary a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the People of GOD, when ever it can be attained, or intertained without Sin: In that Caſe, at all times <hi>Opinionum varietas, &amp; opinantium <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas,</hi> may well conſiſt. Which Truth is founded upon Scripture Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153033:22"/>Promiſes, and Precedents, Commanding, Confirming, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending the Duties of mutual Love, Reconciliation, Peace, Union, and Communion, among the People of GOD, even when there were ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Diſſentions, Faintings, Faillings, Offences, Corruptions, and Defections, among them, in ſeveral circumſtances, nowayes involving the Joyners in ſin. But ſo it is, in the preſent circumſtances; We may have ſuch Union and Communion, without partaking of their guilt, with whom we joyn. For the ſins and ſcandals that ſcarred us from this benefite, in times of defection and diviſion, are ſo far happily removed and antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that they are neither eſtabliſhed in the Conſtitution of the Church, nor ratified and approven in Acts of <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> nor perſiſted in by preſent Adminiſtrations, nor any way affecting Miniſterial Exerciſes; nor do they continue to be our Snares, and Stumbling-blocks, either to involve us in the guilt of them, or to keep us ſtill jangling about them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently muſt ceaſe to be grounds of Separation, There is now no part of the <hi>Presbyterian Miniſtry,</hi> that in Miniſterial Exerciſes is hampered with, or has any dependence on Exotick <hi>Eraſtian</hi> Uſurpations: None of their Meetings do now hold their Freedom from, nor are modified by the <hi>Supremacy,</hi> or any encroaching power: And therefore in our preſent Communion, we keep our ſelves free of all Participation with theſe Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions now removed. And our <hi>Joyning</hi> can not ſo much as be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted a Submitting to, or Complying with any Defection directly or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly. Its true, the guilt of theſe Defections remains, as long as they are not acknowledged; but the eſtabliſhment of them, the practiſe of them, the preſent offence and tentation of them, does not remain. It remains to be their guilt, that will not acknowledge them; and they that are convinced of the guilt of them, and will not confeſs, ſo far as they are convinced, from ſearching the Scriptures, and their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciences, ſhew themſelves no Friends to the Churches peace. But if, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will not hear, our Soul ſhall weep in ſecret places, &amp; as we are called, we do not omit a witneſs againſt theſe Defections, the want of that Confeſſion, through want of Conviction, of the ſinfulneſs of theſe Courſes offending us, can neither be a Sin to us, nor a ground of Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, being only a difference of judgement, which we alwayes diſclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be a ground of withdrawing.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It was alwayes our Judgement and Intention, that when ever Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterial Government, in its Courts, Power, Order, and Freedom were eſtabliſhed, we ſhould ſubmit to it: Nay it was not only our reſolution, but our Engagement, at the Renewing of the Covenants, that we ſhould
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:153033:23"/>not Separate <hi>From any part of the Communion of the true Reformed Covenanted Church of</hi> Scotland, <hi>holding purely and intirely, the Doctoine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Government of the ſame, in Principle and Exerciſe, according to the Rules of Chriſt, and ſtanding Acts and Conſtitutions of this Churth. And that then we ſhould ſtudy to maintain <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Communion, in Truth and Duty, with all the Miniſters and Members of this Church, that do, And in ſo far as they do follow the Inſtitutions of Chriſt. And that when they return unto, and fix their ground on the old eſtabliſhed Foundations, according to the Word of God, &amp; Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this Church ſettled before the Covenanted Reformation ſtopped, we ſhould then embrace and maintaine</hi> Union <hi>and</hi> Communion <hi>with them, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to them in the LORD.</hi> But ſo it is, that all the Ordinances of Chriſt are eſtabliſhed in Purity and Freedom. The <hi>Doctrine,</hi> is aſſerted, in the Confeſſion of Faith, now ratified in Parliament, and ſeveral controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Truths formerly obſcured by Calumnies, are now victoriouſly vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated. The <hi>Worſhip</hi> now, not Tolerated, but Eſtabliſhed and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized, and Adminiſtred in Purity, Plenty, and Peace; and the Lights of the Church are no more hide under Beds or Buſhells, but ſet and ſhinning on the Candleſtick, to give light to all that are in the Houſe: And the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> Presbyterial is now reſtored to what it was <hi>anno</hi> 1592. Wherefore we muſt needs return to our Ancient Union, Communion and Order, when the Church is now returned to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment and eſtabliſhment of her Ancient Conſtitutions, when the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latick, Eraſtian, Antichriſtian and Tyrannical Uſurpations on the Churches Rights, and the Defections and Corruptions flowing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from and introduced thereby are removed, And the Churches intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick Power and Capacity to remove legally all remaining Offences is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored and redintegrated, we could not but ſubmit our ſelves, &amp; pay that deference to <hi>Eccleſiaſtick Judicatories,</hi> fenced in the Name of our only Head and King <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as to ſubject our ſelves to them. We never owned a diviſion from the Church, but only from a party carrying on defection, in a broken and declining State of the Church, and therefore when the Church is not now in that State, but recovering her freedom from theſe breaches &amp; backſlidings, we could not now maintain ſuch a divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. As long as they were involved in, and promoting courſes of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, we ſtood aloof, but now when they are promoting Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, in aſſerting the Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and oppoſing Popery, Prelacy, Eraſtianiſm, Sectarianiſm, and what is contrare to ſound Doctrine, and the power of Godlineſs, we could not but joyn with them. Its true ſeveral Corruptions yet remain
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:153033:23"/>unreformed, as ſome of the former are not condemned: But as all thoſe Corruptions, on which we founded our Separation, becauſe of the hazard of our partaking of the guilt of them, are removed; So we could not ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpend our Union and Communion, until thoſe that remain ſhould be Reformed, and the former Condemned, but rather thought it expedient to Unite, that they may be the ſoonner Reformed; as it is more probable we may ſooner obtain a Reformation of the preſent, and a Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of paſt Corruptions in an United way, then in a Divided way. Its fooliſh to expect the Church can be ſettled without Corruptions, all at once, in one Day or one Year, but muſt crave time, as the building of <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple, and the ſecond Temple, after the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, which was not accompliſhed in ſeveral years: Nor can it be plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over again all at once, no more then in <hi>Joſhuas</hi> dayes, or the Judges, or in the time of the Reforming Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> untill the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> &amp; other Enemies be ſubdued; Nor can it be purged totally altogether, but gradually, leſt it be in hazard of a Superpurgation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It was ever our Judgement, that Diviſion was a great Miſery, and when Unneceſſary and Unſeaſonable, a great Sin: And even when we could not avoid it, we were weary of it, and Longed and Prayed for a time of healing, and an opportunity of bringing it to a Cloſe. But if ever there was a time, when Diviſion was a Miſery and a Sin, becauſe Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary and Unſeaſonable, now it is; And if ever there was an opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of healing, now there is: When the Cauſes and Occaſions of our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions are removed and antiquated; When the Object of them, is ſo far altered that the providences of this day, call and encourage, all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided Parties among <hi>Presbyterians</hi> to contend together for the common Reformation againſt the Common Adverſarie. When the ſad effects of them have made all the Godly weary of them; And the future effects of their Continuance at this time more to be feared then ever, when the wicked Contrivances of Enemies to Divide and Deſtroy the Church, and hinder its Reformation, are ſo many and mighty; When Errors and Ignorance making the People a prey, are ſo abounding: When al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the proper Remedy of them is now in our offer, having a Nail grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us in the holy place to ſet up the Houſe of our God, and to repair the Deſolations thereof, by acceſs to <hi>Aſſemblies:</hi> And when things are now come ſo ſuch a Chock and Criſis, that if there be not preſent application of the Remedy, and ſome Endeavours uſed for Union, now in the tide of it, the breach in all probability will grow wider, and more incurable. When we conſidered both the Mercies of the times, the Maters of praiſe,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:153033:24"/>bringing forth ſo many conſiderable Advantages to the Cauſe, and our ſelvs, we could not but think our ſelves called to another Work, than breaking what God is healing, and retarding the Work by our Diviſions: And when we conſidered the Miſeries of the times, and matters of Mourning, the Paſt and Preſent Cauſes and Effects of the Lords anger, burning up &amp; like to conſume this Church and Kingdom, we could not but ſee other work ſhapen out to us, than this byting and devouring one another, when the Lord in his holy Judgements, &amp; the Antichriſtian Party, in their wicked deſigns are threatening to devout us all.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We were alwayes of the opinion, that <hi>Holy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> was a neceſſary duty, and comfortable Bleſſing, being ſo frequently Commanded, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, Promiſed, and Prayed for as a Bleſſing, and the want of it, threatned and lamented as a Miſery in Scripture: And as we alwayes prayed for it, and longed for it, and bemoaned the miſs of it, ſo we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes deſired that it ſhould be, and waited until we obtained acceſs to get it qualified as the Scripture requires it, that it might be both happy &amp; holy, and as <hi>Aarons</hi> precious Oyntment, that ran down to the skirts of his Garments, compoſed according to Divine Art, made up, not of carnal and corrupt politicks, in a ſinful Confederacy or Conſpiracy for Defection, but compoſed of Goſpel Simples, by the wiſdom, which is from above, firſt pure, then peaceable, that it might be in the Lord, and for the Lord, in Truth and Holineſs, having pure Love for its motive, Bond and Beauty, Chriſt for its Foundation, and His Word for its Rule. But thô we could not get every thing in this preſent <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> that might make it Comfortable and Acceptable to all, nor every thing removed, that is Gravaminous, and impairs its Comfort; Yet we know nothing in the matter of it, which is offenſive, upon the account of its ſinfulneſs. For it will abide the trial of theſe repuired Qualifications: It is not an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of Confederacy in Complyance with wicked Uſurpations, but in ſubjection to the Churches Intrinſick Power and in the uſe and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Churches Liberties: It is not an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of Conſpiracy in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, but in Endeavours to promote Reformation: It is not an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in, or with, or under <hi>Prelacy, Supremacy,</hi> or <hi>Tyranny, Indulgence,</hi> or <hi>Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp;c.</hi> but in, and with, and under <hi>Presbyterial Government,</hi> which is an holy ordinance of Chriſt. It is not an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> that obſtructs any Duty, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goes any Truth, or involves us in any ſin: It is not an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with ſin, thô it be of Sinners with Sinners, now mutually returned to their Common Duties. All the Common Rules of approven Union agree in this: There is no ground of Diviſion ſtanding, which could warrant a breach, if
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:153033:24"/>there had been none before, and therefore there is no ground to continue it in the preſent circumſtances. There is nothing in it, to involve us, in the guilt of paſt or preſent ſins of the time. There is nothing in it, oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to condemn Duty or juſtify ſin, or reſtraining us from any Duty, we are called to. We were neither required to juſtify defections, nor to Condemn our Teſtimonies againſt them; Nor to ſubſcribe to any ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Impoſition, in the termes of Communion, putting us in hazard of partaking with any ſin. On the Contrare, we were allowed to exhibite our Remonſtrance and Teſtimony, againſt all the paſt or preſent Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, ſtumbling to us. And no other Baſis is ſtated, whereupon we <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite,</hi> but the Word of God, Confeſſions of faith, Books of Diſcipline Acts of General Aſſemblies, National and Solemn Covenants, and the whole Contexture of the ancient Order of this Church.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We alwayes thought indeed a Teſtimony was needful, againſt all the defections of the time, and that this was not to be receded from nor buried in oblivion; We are of the ſame mind ſtill. And if <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> could not have been obtained, on any other terms, than ſuch as impoſed the receding from, or condemning of our former Teſtimony againſt Defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we would neither have ſought it, nor embraced it. But as the particular Teſtimony, of every time, in ſeveral reſpects muſt change with the times, according as the Enemies of Truth change their aſſaults &amp; Weapons againſt it, and defections from it, perverſions of it, and contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to it, do vary. And as it can never be buried ſo long as all Truths and Duties are witneſſed for, and errors and ſins are witneſſed againſt by us, in our reſpective ſtations; And nothing is condemned by us, that was approved before, nor approved that was Condemned before, and there is no Engagement to forebear any Duty: So having been allowed to exhibite our <hi>Teſtimony</hi> to an <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> in a more publick manner, than ever we had acceſs before, and being not required nor reſolved, to alter the matter of our Teſtimony, only the manner of it by Separation; We think our preſent <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> and <hi>Submiſſion,</hi> is ſo far from burying our Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt defections, that it tends much for its honour, to give occaſion of recording it, that ſuch a People continued it alwayes, under all diſcouragements and difficulties, while deffections ſtood; But as ſoon as ever they found themſelves in any Capacity to joyne with the Miniſtrie without ſin, they had ſuch reſpect to the Ordinances, and the peace of the Church, that they would no longer Separate, notwithſtanding all former provocations. On the other hand we think to continue Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Separtion at the time, would tend rather to the Scandal and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:153033:25"/>Reproach of all our former witneſſings, than to the ſtrengthening of the ſame, for it might verifie what uſed to be alleged againſt us, that we main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſuch principles as would diſſolve all Union &amp; Order in the world. The beſt Confutation of which reproach, is now to make the contrare appear, by Union, as ſoon as ever we have gor a fond for it. Which now there is, when we have all one common Teſtimony againſt <hi>Papery, Prelacy, Eraſtianiſme, Tyrannie</hi> and <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and every thing contrary to ſound Doctrine, and the Power of Godlineſs.</p>
            <closer>PEACE be within JER<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SALEMS WALLS, and PROSPERITY within her PALLACES.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
